<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="CMH1">1 \n
        ASSESS FOR DEVELOPMENTAL DISORDERS \n
        Assess all domains – motor, cognitive, social, communication, and adaptive. \n
        >>For toddlers and young children: \n
          Has the child had any difficulties with ageappropriate milestones across all developmental areas? \n
        >>For older children and adolescents: \n
          Are there difficulties with school (learning, reading, and writing), communicating and interacting with others,
        self-care, and everyday household activities?
    </string>

    <string-array name="CMH_Asse_Yes">
    <item>
        1 \n
        ASSESS FOR DEVELOPMENTAL DISORDERS \n
        Assess all domains – motor, cognitive, social, communication, and adaptive. \n
        >>For toddlers and young children: \n
          Has the child had any difficulties with ageappropriate milestones across all developmental areas? \n
        >>For older children and adolescents: \n
          Are there difficulties with school (learning, reading, and writing), communicating and interacting with others,
        self-care, and everyday household activities?
    </item>
        <item>
    Suspect DEVELOPMENTAL DELAY / DISORDER \n
    Are there signs/symptoms suggesting any of the following: \n
    – Nutritional deficiency, including iodine deficiency \n
    – Anaemia \n
    – Malnutrition \n
    – Acute or chronic infectious illness, including ear infection and HIV/AIDS
</item>

        <item>
    >>Manage conditions using Integrated Management of Childhood Illness (IMCI) \n
            (www.who.int/maternal_child_adolescent/documents/ IMCI_chartbooklet) or other available guidelines.
    For vision assessment, see if the child fails to: \n
    –  Look at your eyes \n
    –  Follow a moving object with the head and eyes \n
    –  Grab an object –  Recognize familiar people \n

   For hearing assessment, see if the child fails to: \n
    –  Turn head to see someone behind them when they speak \n
    –  Show reaction to loud noise \n
    –  Make a lot of different sounds (tata, dada, baba), if an infant.
</item>

        <item>
    CONSULT WITH SPECIALIST FOR EVALUATION. \n
    Go to PROTOCOL 1 \n \n
    2 \n
    ASSESS FOR PROBLEMS WITH  INATTENTION OR HYPERACTIVITY \n
    Is the child/adolescent: \n
    – Overactive? – Unable to stay still for long? \n
    – Easily distracted, has difficulty completing tasks? \n
            – Moving restlessly? \n

</item>

        <item>
    Are symptoms persistent, severe, and causing considerable dif?culty with daily functioning? Are ALL of the following true? \n
    – Are symptoms present in multiple settings? \n
    – Have they lasted at least 6 months? \n
    – Are they inappropriate for the child/ adolescent’s developmental level? \n
    – Is there considerable dif?culty with daily functioning in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other areas?
</item>

        <item>
    Consider ADHD \n
    Rule out physical conditions that can resemble ADHD. Does the child/adolescent have any of the following: \n
    – Thyroid diseases \n
    – Acute or chronic infectious illness, including HIV/AIDS \n
    – Uncontrolled pain e.g. from an ear infection, sickle cell disease \n

</item>

        <item>
    Treat the physical condition \n
    >>Go to PROTOCOL 3 \n \n
    3 \n
    ASSESS FOR CONDUCT DISORDER \n
    Does the child/adolescent show repeated aggressive, disobedient, or de?ant behaviour, for example: \n
    – Arguing with adults \n
    – Defying or refusing to comply with their requests or rules \n
    – Extreme irritability/anger \n
    – Frequent and severe temper tantrums \n
    – Dif?culty getting along with others \n
    – Provocative behaviour \n
    – Excessive levels of ?ghting or bullying \n
    – Cruelty to animals or people \n
    – Severe destructiveness to property, ?re-setting \n
    – Stealing, repeated lying, truancy from school, running away from home

</item>

        <item>
    Are symptoms persistent, severe, and inappropriate for the  child/adolescent’s developmental level: \n
    –  Symptoms are present in different settings (e.g. at home, at school and in other social settings). \n
    –   Symptoms have been present for at least 6 months. \n
    –  More severe than ordinary childish mischief or adolescent rebelliousness. \n
    –  Is there considerable dif?culty with daily functioning in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other areas? \n
</item>

        <item>
    Consider CONDUCT DISORDER \n
    >>Go to PROTOCOL 4 \n \n
    4 \n
    ASSESS FOR EMOTIONAL DISORDERS  (prolonged, disabling distress involving sadness, fearfulness, anxiety or irritability) \n
    Ask if the child/adolescent: \n
    – Is often feeling irritable, easily annoyed, down or sad? \n
    – Has lost interest in or enjoyment of activities? \n
    – Has many worries or often seems worried? \n
    – Has many fears or is easily scared? \n
    – Often complains of headaches, stomach-aches or sickness? \n
    – Is often unhappy, down-hearted or tearful? \n
    –  Avoids or strongly dislikes certain situations (e.g. separation  from carers, meeting new people, or closed spaces)?
</item>

        <item>
    Is there considerable difficulty with daily functioning in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other areas? \n

</item>

        <item>
    Consider EMOTIONAL DISORDER \n
    Rule out physical conditions that can resemble or exacerbate emotional disorders \n
    Are there any signs/symptoms suggesting: \n
    – Thyroid diseases \n
    – Infectious illness,  including HIV/AIDS \n
    – Anaemia \n
    – Obesity \n
    – Malnutrition \n
    – Asthma \n
    –  Medication side-effects  (e.g. from corticosteroids or   inhaled asthma medications)

</item>

        <item>
    Manage the physical condition. \n
    In adolescents, assess for moderate to severe depression. \n
    Does the adolescent have problems with mood (feeling irritable, down or sad)  OR has lost interest in or enjoyment of activities? \n
</item>

        <item>
    Has the adolescent had several of the following additional symptoms most days for the last 2 weeks? \n
    –  Disturbed sleep or sleeping too much \n
    –  Significant change in appetite or weight (decrease or increase) \n
    –  Beliefs of worthlessness or excessive guilt \n
    –  Fatigue or loss of energy \n
    –  Reduced concentration \n
    –  Indecisiveness \n
    –  Observable agitation or physical restlessness \n
    –  Talking or moving more slowly than usual \n
    –  Hopelessness \n
    –  Suicidal thoughts or acts \n

    Is there considerable dif?culty with daily functioning in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other areas?
</item>
        <item>
    Consider DEPRESSION \n
    Rule out a history of manic episode(s) and normal reaction to recent major loss. See » DEP. \n
    >>Go to PROTOCOL 6 \n \n

    5 \n
    ASSESS FOR OTHER PRIORITY MNS CONDITIONS \n

    Are there any other concurrent MNS conditions? Assess according to the  mhGAP-IG Master Chart. See » MC. \n
    Do not forget to assess for disorders due to substance use. See » SUB. \n
    For children with developmental delay/disorders, do not forget to assess for epilepsy. See » EPI.
</item>

        <item>
    ASSESS AND MANAGE concurrent MNS conditions \n
    6 \n
    ASSESS THE HOME ENVIRONMENT \n
    Are the emotional, behavioural or developmental problems a reaction to or aggravated by a distressing or frightening situation? \n
    Assess for: \n
    Clinical features or any element in the clinical history that suggest maltreatment or exposure to violence (see CLINICAL TIP). \n
    Any recent or ongoing severe stressors (e.g. illness or death of a family member, difficult living and financial circumstances, being bullied or harmed). \n

</item>

        <item>
    >>Refer to child protection services if necessary  \n
    >>Explore and manage stressors \n
    >>Ensure child/adolescent’s safety as a ?rst priority  \n
    >>Reassure the child/adolescent that all children/adolescents need to  be protected from abuse \n
    >>Provide information about where to seek help for any ongoing abuse \n
    >>Arrange additional support including referral to specialist \n
    >>Contact legal and community resources, as appropriate and as mandated  \n
    >>Consider additional psychosocial interventions  \n
    >>Ensure appropriate follow-up \n \n

    Do the carers have any priority MNS condition that could impact their ability to care for the child/adolescent?
    Consider especially depression and disorders due to substance use.
</item>

        <item>
   >> Assess and manage for carer  MNS conditions. \n
   >> Go to Management 2.6 (Carer support)
</item>

        <item>
    >>Provide advise on age-appropriate stimulation and parenting. Refer to Care for Child Development http://www.who.int/maternal_ child_adolescent/documents/care_child_ development/en/  \n
    >>Consider need for additional support for the  child including referral to child protection services where available.
</item>

        <item>
    7 \n
    ASSESS THE SCHOOL ENVIRONMENT \n
    Is the child/adolescent in school?

</item>

        <item>
    Is the child/adolescent: \n
    >>Being bullied, picked on or made fun of? \n
    >>Not able to participate and learn?  \n
    >>Not wanting/refusing to attend school?

</item>

        <item>
    >>After getting consent, liaise with teachers and other school staff. Go to Management (2.7). \n
    >>If there has been an absence from school,  try to help the child/adolescent return to school as soon as possible and explore reasons for absence.

</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="CMH_Asse_No">

        <item>
            SKIP to STEP  2
        </item>
        <item>
            2 \n
    ASSESS FOR PROBLEMS WITH  INATTENTION OR HYPERACTIVITY \n
    Is the child/adolescent: \n
    – Overactive? – Unable to stay still for long? \n
    – Easily distracted, has difficulty completing tasks? \n
            – Moving restlessly? \n
        </item>

        <item>
    Assess the child for visual and/or hearing impairment: \n
    For vision assessment, see if the child fails to: \n
    –  Look at your eyes  \n
    –  Follow a moving object with the head and eyes \n
    –  Grab an object \n
    –  Recognize familiar people \n

    For hearing assessment, see if the child fails to: \n
    –  Turn head to see someone behind them when they speak \n
    –  Show reaction to loud noise \n
    –  Make a lot of different sounds (tata, dada, baba), if an infant
</item>

        <item>
    >>Go to PROTOCOL 1
</item>

        <item>
    SKIP to STEP  3
    </item>
        <item>
             3 \n
    ASSESS FOR CONDUCT DISORDER \n
    Does the child/adolescent show repeated aggressive, disobedient, or de?ant behaviour, for example: \n
    – Arguing with adults \n
    – Defying or refusing to comply with their requests or rules \n
    – Extreme irritability/anger \n
    – Frequent and severe temper tantrums \n
    – Dif?culty getting along with others \n
    – Provocative behaviour \n
    – Excessive levels of ?ghting or bullying \n
    – Cruelty to animals or people \n
    – Severe destructiveness to property, ?re-setting \n
    – Stealing, repeated lying, truancy from school, running away from home
        </item>
        <item>
    CONDUCT DISORDER  is unlikely \n
    SKIP to STEP   4
</item>

        <item>
    ADHD  is unlikely \n
    Consider  PROBLEMS WITH BEHAVIOUR \n
    >> Go to PROTOCOL 2 \n
    SKIP to STEP  3
        </item>

        <item>
    >>Go to PROTOCOL 3
</item>

        <item>
    4 \n
    ASSESS FOR EMOTIONAL DISORDERS  (prolonged, disabling distress involving sadness, fearfulness, anxiety or irritability) \n
    Ask if the child/adolescent: \n
    – Is often feeling irritable, easily annoyed, down or sad? \n
    – Has lost interest in or enjoyment of activities? \n
    – Has many worries or often seems worried? \n
    – Has many fears or is easily scared? \n
    – Often complains of headaches, stomach-aches or sickness? \n
    – Is often unhappy, down-hearted or tearful? \n
    –  Avoids or strongly dislikes certain situations (e.g. separation  from carers, meeting new people, or closed spaces)?
</item>

        <item>
    SKIP to STEP  5
</item>

        <item>
    Consider  PROBLEMS WITH EMOTIONS \n
    >>Go to PROTOCOL 5 \n
    SKIP to STEP  5
</item>

        <item>
    Go to PROTOCOL 6 \n
    In adolescents, assess for moderate to severe depression. \n
    Does the adolescent have problems with mood (feeling irritable, down or sad)  OR has lost interest in or enjoyment of activities?
</item>

        <item>
   5 \n
    ASSESS FOR OTHER PRIORITY MNS CONDITIONS \n

    Are there any other concurrent MNS conditions? Assess according to the  mhGAP-IG Master Chart. See » MC. \n
    Do not forget to assess for disorders due to substance use. See » SUB. \n
    For children with developmental delay/disorders, do not forget to assess for epilepsy. See » EPI.
</item>

        <item>
    Consider  PROBLEMS WITH EMOTIONS \n
    >> Go to PROTOCOL 5 \n
    SKIP to STEP  5

</item>

        <item>
    6 \n
    ASSESS THE HOME ENVIRONMENT \n
    Are the emotional, behavioural or developmental problems a reaction to or aggravated by a distressing or frightening situation? \n
    Assess for: \n
    Clinical features or any element in the clinical history that suggest maltreatment or exposure to violence (see CLINICAL TIP). \n
    Any recent or ongoing severe stressors (e.g. illness or death of a family member, dif?cult living and ?nancial circumstances, being bullied or harmed). \n

</item>

        <item>
    Do the carers have any priority MNS condition that could impact their ability to care for the child/adolescent? \n
    Consider especially depression and disorders due to substance use.

</item>

        <item>
    Is the child getting adequate opportunities for play and social interaction/communication at home? \n
    Consider asking: \n
   >> With whom does the child spend most of their time?  \n
    >>How do you/they play with the child? How often?   \n
    >>How do you/they communicate with the child? How often?

</item>

        <item>
    7 \n
    ASSESS THE SCHOOL ENVIRONMENT \n
    Is the child/adolescent in school?

</item>

        <item>
    >>Provide information regarding educational services and educate carer on importance of keeping the child/adolescent in school as much as possible.
</item>

        <item>
    >>Go to CMH 2 (Management)
</item>
        <item>
            Are there signs/symptoms suggesting any of the following:  \n
            –  Nutritional deﬁciency, including iodine deﬁciency
            – Anaemia \n
            – Malnutrition \n
            –  Acute or chronic infectious illness, including ear infection and HIV/AIDS \n
        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string name="cmhfollow1">
        1 \n
    ASSESS FOR IMPROVEMENT \n
    Is the person improving? \n
    Reassess and monitor the child/adolescent’s symptoms, behaviour, and functioning at every visit.
    </string>

    <string-array name="CMH_FolowUp_Yes">

<item>
    1 \n
    ASSESS FOR IMPROVEMENT \n
    Is the person improving? \n
    Reassess and monitor the child/adolescent’s symptoms, behaviour, and functioning at every visit.

</item>

        <item>
        »  Continue with management plan and follow-up  until symptoms cease or remit. \n
        »  Provide additional psychoeducation and advice on parenting. \n
        »  If on medication, consider gradually reducing medication dose in consultation with a specialist. \n
        »  If not on medication, decrease frequency of  follow up once symptoms have subsided and the child/adolescent is able to perform well in daily life.
    </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="CMH_FolowUp_No">
<item>
    »  Provide additional psychoeducation and advice on parenting, as appropriate.  \n
    »  Review psychosocial interventions and revise management plan as needed.  Involve child/adolescent and carers in decision-making, as appropriate. \n
    » Offer regular follow-up. \n \n

    If NO improvement in symptoms and/or functioning in 6 months: \n
    »  Provide additional interventions if available. \n
    »   Increase the frequency of follow-up visits as needed. \n
    »  REFER TO SPECIALIST if available, for further assessment and management. \n \n

        DEVELOPMENTAL DISORDERS
        If no improvement, further deterioration, predicted danger to the  child, or physical health is affected (such as nutritional problems), \n
        »  REFER TO SPECIALIST for further assessment and advice on management plan.  \n
        DO NOT consider pharmacological treatment. \n \n

        ADHD
        If no improvement and the child is at least 6 years old and has  received psychosocial treatment for at least 6 months  \n
        »  Refer to or consult SPECIALIST for methylphenidate use. \n \n

        CONDUCT DISORDERS
        If no improvemen or predicted danger to the adolescent \n
        »  REFER TO SPECIALIST for further assessment and advice  on management plan.  \n
        DO NOT consider pharmacological treatment. \n \n

        EMOTIONAL DISORDERS
        If no improvement and the child/adolescent has received psychosocial treatment for at least 6 months \n
        »  REFER TO SPECIALIST.  \n
        DO NOT initiate pharmacological treatment. \n \n

        DEPRESSION
        If no improvement and the adolescent is 12 years or older and  has received psychosocial treatment for at least 6 months \n
        »  Refer to or consult SPECIALIST for fluoxetine (but not other  SSRIs or TCAs). \n \n

       2 \n
        <b>  CONDUCT ROUTINE ASSESSMENTS </b>\n

        At every visit: \n
        »  For children under 5 years, monitor child development. \n
        »  Assess for the presence of any new problem or symptom related to mood, behaviour or development/learning. For adolescents, assess for the presence of worsening mood (irritable, easily annoyed or frustrated, down or sad) or suicidal thoughts.  Go back to Assessment Step 4 for worsening mood. Go to » SUI for suicidal thoughts. \n
        »  Explore and address psychosocial stressors in the home, school  or work environment, including exposure to violence or other forms of maltreatment. \n
        »  Assess opportunities for the child/adolescent to participate  in family and social life. \n
        »  Assess carers’ needs and support available to the family. \n
        »  Monitor attendance at school. \n
        »  Review management plan and monitor adherence to psychosocial interventions. \n
        »  If on medication, review adherence, side-effects, and dosing. \n \n

        3 \n
        <b> MONITOR PHARMACOLOGICAL TREATMENT AS APPLICABLE </b> \n

        Additional monitoring if the adolescent  has been prescribed fluoxetine \n

        >> Record prescription and administration details. \n
        >> Weekly for the first month, then every month: \n
           monitor for reported side-effects and changes in mood and other symptoms. \n
        >>Consult specialist if you identify severe medication sideeffects or adverse events (e.g. new or worsening suicidal thoughts, suicidal or self-harming behaviour, agitation, irritability, anxiety or insomnia). \n
        >>Advise the adolescent to continue the medication even if they feel better. The medication should be continued for 9-12 months after the symptoms have resolved to reduce the risk of relapse. \n
        >>Advise against suddenly stopping the medication. \n
        >>If symptoms have been resolved for 9-12 months: \n
          Discuss with adolescent and carer risks and benefits to taper off medication. Reduce treatment gradually over minimum 4 weeks, monitor closely for symptom recurrence. \n \n


        Additional monitoring if the child has  been prescribed methylphenidate \n

        >> Record prescription and administration details. \n
        >> Monitor potential for misuse and diversion. \n
        >> Every three months: monitor/record height, weight, blood pressure, reported side-effects, and changes in behaviour. \n
        >> Consult specialist if you observe medication side-effects  (e.g. failure to make expected gains in weight and height, increased blood pressure, agitation, anxiety, and severe insomnia). \n
        >> After one year of treatment: Consult specialist regarding the continuation of methylphenidate.

    </item>

    </string-array>
</resources>