
<resources>
    <string name="fst">1) \n
            Does the person have depression? \n
            Has the person had at least one of the following core symptoms of depression for at least 2 weeks?\n\n
            - Persistent depressed mood \n
            - Markedly diminished interest in or pleasure from activities
    </string>
    <string-array name="yq">
        <item> 1) \n
            Does the person have depression? \n
            Has the person had at least one of the following core symptoms of depression for at least 2 weeks?\n\n
            - Persistent depressed mood \n
            - Markedly diminished interest in or pleasure from activities
        </item>

        <item>Has the person had several of the following additional symptoms  for at least 2 weeks:\n\n
            –  Disturbed sleep or sleeping too much \n
            –  Signiﬁcant change in appetite or weight (decrease or increase) \n
            –  Beliefs of worthlessness or excessive guilt \n
            –  Fatigue or loss of energy \n
            –  Reduced concentration\n
            –  Indecisiveness \n
            –  Observable agitation or physical restlessness \n
            –  Talking or moving more slowly than usual –  Hopelessness \n
            –  Suicidal thoughts or acts

        </item>
        <item>Does the person have considerable difﬁculty with
            daily functioning in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other areas?\n\n
        </item>

        <item> 2) \n
            <b>Consider DEPRESSION</b>\n
            Are there other possible explanations  for the symptoms?
            IS THIS A PHYSICAL CONDITION THAT CAN RESEMBLE OR EXACERBATE DEPRESSION? \n\n
            Are there signs and symptoms suggesting anaemia, malnutrition,  hypothyroidism,
            mood changes from substance use and medication side-effects  (e.g. mood changes from steroids)
        </item>
        <item>  - MANAGE THE PHYSICAL CONDITION \n\n
            Do depressive symptoms remain after treatment?
        </item>
        <item> <b>IS THERE A HISTORY OF MANIA? </b>\n
            Have several of the following symptoms occurred simultaneously, lasting for at least 1 week, and
            severely enough to interfere signiﬁcantly with work and social activities or requiring hospitalization or
            conﬁnement? \n
            – Elevation of mood and/or irritability \n
            – Decreased need for sleep \n
            –  Increased activity, feeling of increased energy, increased  talkativeness or rapid speech \n
            –  Impulsive or reckless behaviours such as excessive spending, making important decisions without
            planning and sexual indiscretion
            – Loss of normal social inhibitions resulting in inappropriate behaviours \n
            – Being easily distracted \n
            – Unrelistically inflated self-esteem \n
        </item>
        <item>DEPRESSIVE EPISODE IN BIPOLAR DISORDER is likely \n\n
               Go to STEP  3  then to PROTOCOL 2 \n
        </item>
        <item>
            Are any of the following symptoms present? \n
            – Suicidal ideation  \n
            – Beliefs of worthlessness \n
            – Psychotic symptoms \n
            – Talking or moving more slowly than nornal
        </item>
        <item> 3) \n
            DEPRESSION is likely \n
        Are there concurrent priority MNS conditions? \n\\n
            Assess for concurrent MNS conditions according to the  mhGAP-IG master chart. Go to » MC.\n
            Go to PROTOCOL 1\n
        </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="nq">
        <item>Depression is unlikely \n
            Go to OTH (Other Significant Disease) </item>
        <item>No Treatment required</item>
        <item> <b>IS THERE A HISTORY OF MANIA? </b>\n
            Have several of the following symptoms occurred simultaneously, lasting for at least 1 week, and
            severely enough to interfere signiﬁcantly with work and social activities or requiring hospitalization or
            conﬁnement? \n
            – Elevation of mood and/or irritability \n
            – Decreased need for sleep \n
            –  Increased activity, feeling of increased energy, increased  talkativeness or rapid speech \n
            –  Impulsive or reckless behaviours such as excessive spending, making important decisions without
            planning and sexual indiscretion
            – Loss of normal social inhibitions resulting in inappropriate behaviours \n
            – Being easily distracted \n
            – Unrelistically inflated self-esteem \n
        </item>
        <item>HAS THERE BEEN A MAJOR LOSS (E.G. BEREAVEMENT)  WITHIN THE LAST 6 MONTHS?</item>
        <item>DEPRESSION is likely \n\n
            Go to STEP  3   then to PROTOCOL
        </item>
        <item>
            Does the person have a previous history of depression?
        </item>
        <item>
            Do not manage for depression. \n\n Go to  OTH
        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="depfollowyes">
        <item>
            1 \n ASSESS FOR IMPROVEMENT \n  Is the person improving?
        </item>
        <item>
            »  Encourage the person to continue with their  current management plan until they are symptom free for 9-12 months. \n\n
            »  Arrange a further follow up appointment  in 1-2 weeks. \n\n
            »  Decrease contact as the person’s symptoms improve, e.g. once every 3 months after the initial 3 months.
               Note: follow up should continue until the person no longer  has any symptoms of depression.
        </item>
        <item>
            2 \n  MONITOR TREATMENT \n <b>At every contact: </b> \n
            »  Provide psychoeducation, reduce stress and strengthen social supports, promote functioning in daily activities and
                community life, and review, if applicable, antidepressant medication use and psychological treatment.  \n
            »  Does the person have any new symptoms of concern? Review for MNS and concurrent physical conditions. \n
            »  Is the person a woman of childbearing age and considering pregnancy? If so, CONSULT A SPECIALIST.   \n
               Assess for any IMMINENT RISK OF SUICIDE (Go to  SUI).\n\n
            3 \n  REVISE TREATMENT AS APPROPRIATE  \n\n
                Has the person been symptom free for 9-12 months? \n
        </item>
        <item>
            »  Discuss with the person the risks and beneﬁts of stopping the medication.\n
            »  Taper the dose of medication gradually, over a minimum of 4 weeks. Monitor the person for symptom recurrence.\n

        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="depfollowno">
        <item>
            »  If not yet receiving psychological treatment,  consider psychological treatment. \n
            »  If receiving a psychological treatment, evaluate engagement in  and experience of current psychological treatment. \n
            »  If not yet on antidepressants, consider antidepressants. \n
            »  If on antidepressants, assess: –  Does the person take the medication as prescribed? If not, explore reasons why and
               encourage adherence.\n
               <b>Are there side effects?</b>
            »   If yes, evaluate and weigh beneﬁts of treatment.  If no to side effects to antidepressants, increase dose (TABLE 1).
               Follow-up in 1-2 weeks. \n
               CAUTION WITH DOSE INCREASE. \n
               CLOSE FOLLOW-UP NEEDED   DUE TO POSSIBLE INCREASE IN SIDE EFFECTS.
        </item>
        <item>
            »  Continue medication until person is  symptom free for 9-12 months.
        </item>
    </string-array>


</resources>