<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="Epl1">
        1 \n
        Has the person had convulsive movements  lasting longer than 1-2 minutes? \n
        Does the person have convulsive seizures? \n
    </string>

    <string-array name="Epilepsy_Assessment_Yes">
       <item>
        1 \n
        Has the person had convulsive movements  lasting longer than 1-2 minutes? \n
        Does the person have convulsive seizures? \n
        </item>

        <item>
        Has the person had at least 2 of the following symptoms during the episode(s)? \n
        –  Loss of consciousness or impaired consciousness \n
        – Stiffness, rigidity \n
        – Bitten or bruised tongue, bodily injury \n
        – Incontinence of faeces/urine \n
        –  After the convulsion: fatigue, drowsiness, sleepiness, confusion, abnormal behaviour, headache, muscle aches, or weakness on one  side of the body \n
        </item>

        <item>
     Suspect CONVULSIVE SEIZURES \n
        2 \n
        Is there an acute cause? \n
        Is there neuroinfection or other possible causes of convulsions? \n
        » Check for signs and symptoms: \n
        – Fever \n
        – Headache \n
        – Confusion \n
        – Meningeal irritation (e.g. stiff neck) \n
        – Head injury \n
        – Metabolic abnormality  (e.g. hypogylcemia/ hyponatremia) \n
        –  Alcohol or drug intoxication or  withdrawal \n
        </item>

        <item>
        » EVALUATE and TREAT MEDICAL CONDITION \n
        »  REFER TO HOSPITAL
        IF POSSIBLE FOR HEAD INJURY, MENINGITIS, AND METABOLIC ABNORMALITIES \n
        ANTIEPILEPTIC MEDICATION  NOT REQUIRED \n
        »  Follow-up in 3 months to  assess for possible epilepsy \n
        </item>

        <item>
        EPILEPSY is likely \n
           Asses for underlying cause. Do a physical examination. \n
           »Are any of the following present? \n
           – Birth asphyxia or trauma history \n
           – Head injury \n
           – Infection of the brain \n
           – Family history of seizures \n
        </item>

        <item>
            »REFER TO SPECIALIST FOR FURTHER EVALUATION OF CAUSE \n
            4 \n
            Are there concurrent MNS conditions? \n
            »Assess for other concurrent MNS conditions according to the  mhGAP-IG Master Chart (MC) \n
        Please note persons with EPILEPSY are at higher risk for DEPRESSION, DISORDERS  DUE TO SUBSTANCE USE. CHILDREN AND ADOLSCENTS MAY HAVE ASSOCIATED MENTAL AND BEHAVIOURAL DISORDERS. SUBSTANCE USE DISORDERS
             Go to PROTOCOL 1 \n
        </item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="Epilepsy_Assessment_No">
        <item>
            Convulsive seizures unlikely \n
            » Consult a specialist for recurrent episodes \n
            » Follow-up in 3 months \n
        </item>

        <item>
            Convulsive seizures unlikely \n
            » Consult a specialist for recurrent episodes \n
            » Follow-up in 3 months \n
        </item>

        <item>
            Suspect EPILEPSY \n
            SKIP to STEP 3 \n \n

            3 \n
            Does the person have epilepsy? \n
            Has the person had at least two seizures on two different days in the past year? \n
        </item>

        <item>
         Does not meet criteria for epilepsy \n
             »Maintenance antiepileptic medication not necessary \n
             »Follow-up in 3 months  and assess for possible epilepsy \n
        </item>


        <item>
        4 \n
            Are there concurrent MNS conditions? \n
            » Assess for other concurrent MNS conditions according to the  mhGAP-IG Master Chart (MC) \n
              Please note persons with EPILEPSY are at higher risk for DEPRESSION, DISORDERS  DUE TO SUBSTANCE USE. CHILDREN
                AND ADOLSCENTS MAY HAVE ASSOCIATED MENTAL AND BEHAVIOURAL DISORDERS. SUBSTANCE USE DISORDERS \n
        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string name="Epifollow">
        1 \n
            REVIEW THE CURRENT CONDITION \n
            Does the person have more than 50% seizure reduction in convulsion frequency? \n
    </string>

    <string-array name="Epi_FollowUp_Yes">
        <item>
            1 \n
            REVIEW THE CURRENT CONDITION \n
            Does the person have more than 50% seizure reduction in convulsion frequency? \n
        </item>

        <item>
          2 \n
            MONITOR TREATMENT \n
            At every contact: \n
            » Evaluate side-effects of medication including adverse effects  and idiosyncratic reactions (clinically and with appropriate laboratory tests when available). \n
            » Provide psychoeducation and review psychosocial interventions. \n
            » Is the person a woman of childbearing age and considering  pregnancy? If so, consult specialist. \n
            » Does the patient have any new symptoms of concern?  Review for any new symptoms of depression and anxiety given
            high risk of co-morbidity with epilepsy. \n
            » Is the patient on any new medications that may have interactions?  (Many anticonvulsants have interactions
            with other medications). If so, consult a specialist. \n \n
            3 \n
            CONSIDER MEDICATION DISCONTINUATION WHEN APPROPRIATE \n
            Has the person been convulsion free for several years? \n
        </item>

        <item>
            » Discuss risk of seizure occurrence with person/carer  (if epilepsy is due to head injury, stroke or neuroinfection, there is a higher risk of seizure recurrence off medication), and risks and beneﬁts of discontinuing medications. \n
            » If in agreement, gradually take the person off  medication by reducing the doses over 2 months and monitoring closely for seizure recurrence. \n
        </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="Epi_FollowUp_No">
        <item>
            IF THE PERSON IS NOT IMPROVING ON CURRENT DOSE: \n
            » Review adherence to medications. \n
            » Consider increase in medication dose as needed to  maximal dose if no adverse effects. \n
            » If response is still poor, \n
            – C onsider switching medication. The new medication should be at an optimum dose before slowly discontinuing the ﬁrst. \n
            » If response is still poor, \n
            – Review diagnosis. \n
            – REFER TO SPECIALIST. \n
            » Follow-up more frequently. \n
        </item>

        <item>
            IF THERE ARE NO PROBLEMS WITH MEDICATIONS \n
            »  Continue at current dose. Correct dosing is lowest therapeutic dose for seizure control, while minimizing adverse side-effects. \n
            »  Continue close follow-up and review for possible discontinuation of medications once seizure free for at least two years. \n
        </item>
    </string-array>

</resources>