
<resources>
    <string-array name="PSY_Asse_Yes">
        <item>
        1 \n
        Are there any other explanations for the symptoms? \n
        EVALUATE FOR MEDICAL CONDITIONS \n
        By history, clinical examination, or laboratory findings, are there signs and symptoms
        suggesting delirium due to an acute physical condition, e.g. infection, cerebral malaria,
        dehydration, metabolic abnormalities (such as hypoglycaemia or hyponatraemia);
        or medication side effects, e.g. due to some antimalarial medication or steroids?
    </item>
        <item>
            Assess and manage the acute physical condition, and refer to emergency services/ specialist as needed.
            If symptoms persist after management of the acute cause, go to STEP 2
        </item>

        <item>
            Consider consultation with a mental health specialist for management of concurrent conditions.
            Manage concurrent conditions.
            Go to relevant modules.
        </item>
        <item>
           2\n
           Is the person having an acute manic episode? \n
            Have several of the following symptoms occurred simultaneously, lasting for at least 1 week, and severely enough
            to interfere significantly with work and social activities or requiring confinement or hospitalization: \n
            – Elevated or irritable mood \n
            – Decreased need for sleep \n
            – Increased activity, feeling of increased energy, increased talkativeness or rapid speech \n
            – Loss of normal social inhibitions such as sexual indiscretion \n
            – Impulsive or reckless behaviours such as excessive spending, making important decisions without planning \n
            – Being easily distracted \n
            – Unrealistically inflated self-esteem \n
        </item>

        <item>
            Suspect \n
            BIPOLAR DISORDER Manic Episode \n
            Go to PROTOCOL 1
        </item>

        <item>
        Suspect \n
        PSYCHOSIS \n
        Go to PROTOCOL 2
        </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="PSY_Asse_No">
        <item>
        » EVALUATE FOR DEMENTIA, DEPRESSION, DRUG/ALCOHOL INTOXICATION OR WITHDRAWAL.
        </item>

        <item>
            2\n
           Is the person having an acute manic episode? \n

            Have several of the following symptoms occurred simultaneously, lasting for at least 1 week, and severely enough
            to interfere significantly with work and social activities or requiring confinement or hospitalization: \n
            – Elevated or irritable mood \n
            – Decreased need for sleep \n
            – Increased activity, feeling of increased energy, increased talkativeness or rapid speech \n
            – Loss of normal social inhibitions such as sexual indiscretion \n
            – Impulsive or reckless behaviours such as excessive spending, making important decisions without planning \n
            – Being easily distracted \n
            – Unrealistically inflated self-esteem \n
        </item>

        <item>
            3\n
            Does the person have psychosis? \n

            Does the person have at least two of the following: \n
            – Delusions, fixed false beliefs not shared by others in the person’s culture \n
            – Hallucinations, hearing voices or seeing things that are not there \n
            – Disorganized speech and/or behaviour,e.g. incoherent/irrelevant speech such as mumbling or laughing to self, strange appearance, signs of self-neglect or appearing unkempt
        </item>

        <item>
            Consider consultation with specialist to review other possible causes of psychoses.
        </item>
    </string-array>


</resources>