<resources>
    <string name="app_name">mhGAP</string>
    <string name="title_activity_home">Home</string>

    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>

    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="title_activity_contactus">Contact Us</string>
    <string name="title_activity_essential">Essential Care</string>
    <string name="title_activity_symbols">Symbols</string>
    <string name="activity_master">Master Chart</string>
    <string name="title_activity_glossery">Glossery</string>
    <string name="title_activity_aboutus">About Us</string>
    <string name="title_activity_help">Help</string>
    <string name="rd">This module outlines the principles of essential care for all people seeking health care, including those
        with MNS conditions, and their carers. The first section of this module covers the general principles of clinical care
        and aims to promote respect for the privacy of people seeking care for MNS conditions, foster good relationships between
        health care providers, service users and their carers, and ensure care is provided in a non-judgmental, non-stigmatizing,
        and supportive manner. The second section covers essentials of mental health clinical practice and aims to present
        healthcare providers with an overview of the assessment and management of MNS conditions in non-specialized settings.
    </string>
    <string-array name="depcontent">
        <item>
        DEPRESSION\n\n
        -> Multiple persistent physical symptoms with no clear cause \n
        -> Low energy, fatigue, sleep problems Persistent sadness or depressed mood, anxiety \n
        -> Loss of interest or pleasure in activities that are normally pleasurable
        </item>

        <item>
        PSYCHOSES\n\n
        -> Marked behavioural changes; neglecting usual responsibilities related to work, school, domestic or social activities
        -> Agitated, aggressive behavior, decreased or increased activity \n
        -> Fixed false beliefs not shared by others in the person’s culture \n
        -> Hearing voices or seeing things that are not there \n
        -> Lack of realization that one is having mental health problems \n
 </item>
        <item>
            EPILEPSY\n\n
        -> Convulsive movement or ﬁts/seizures \n
        -> During the convulsion: loss of consciousness or impaired consciousness, stiffness, rigidity, tongue bite, injury,
        incontinence of urine or faeces \n
        -> After the convulsion: fatigue, drowsiness, sleepiness, confusion, abnormal behaviour, headache, muscle aches, or
        weakness on one side of the body \n
        </item>
        <item>CMH BEHAVIOURAL DISORDER\n\n
        -> Child/adolescent being seen for physical complaints or a general health assessment who has: \n
        -> Problem with development, emotions or behaviour (e.g. inattention, over-activity, or repeated deﬁant, disobedient and
           aggressive behaviour) \n
        -> Risk factors such as malnutrition, abuse and/or neglect, frequent illness, chronic diseases (e.g. HIV/AIDS or history
           of difﬁcult birth) \n
        -> Carer with concerns about the child/adolescent’s: \n
        -> Difﬁculty keeping up with peers or carrying out daily activities considered normal for age \n
        -> Behaviour (e.g. too active, aggressive, having frequent and/or severe tantrums, wanting to be alone too much,
        refusing to do regular activities or go to school) \n
        -> Teacher with concerns about a child/adolescent \n
        -> e.g. easily distracted, disruptive in class, often getting into trouble, difﬁculty completing school work \n\n
        Community health or social services worker with concerns about a child/adolescent \n
        -> e.g. rule- or law-breaking behaviour, physical aggression at home or in the community \n
        </item>
        <item>DEMENTIA\n\n
        -> Decline or problems with memory (severe forgetfulness) and orientation (awareness of time, place and person) \n
        -> Mood or behavioural problems such as apathy (appearing uninterested) or irritability \n
        -> Loss of emotional control (easily upset, irritable or tearful) Difﬁculties in carrying out usual work, domestic or
        social activities \n
        </item>
        <item>SUBSTANCE USE\n\n
        -> Appearing affected by alcohol or other substance (e.g. smell of alcohol, slurred speech, sedated, erratic
        behaviour) \n
        -> Signs and symptoms of acute behavioural effects, withdrawal features or effects of prolonged use \n
        -> Deterioration of social functioning (i.e. difﬁculties at work or home, unkempt appearance) \n
        -> Signs of chronic liver disease (abnormal liver enzymes), jaundiced (yellow) skin and eyes, palpable and tender liver
        edge (in early liver disease), ascites (distended abdomen is ﬁlled with ﬂuid), spider naevi (spider-like blood vessels
        visible on the surface of the skin), and altered mental status (hepatic encephalopathy) \n
        -> Problems with balance, walking, coordinated movements, and nystagmus \n
        -> Incidental ﬁndings: macrocytic anaemia, low platelet count, elevated mean corpuscular volume (MCV) \n
        -> Emergency presentation due to substance withdrawal, overdose, or intoxication. Person may appear sedated,
        overstimulated, agitated, anxious or confused"\n"> Persons with disorders due to substance use may not report any
        problems with substance use. Look for:"\n"\t – Recurrent requests for psychoactive medications including analgesics \n
        \t – Injuries \n \t – Infections associated with intravenous drug use (HIV/AIDS, Hepatitis C) \n
        </item>
        <item>SELF-HARM/SUICIDE\n\n
        -> Extreme hopelessness and despair \n
        -> Current thoughts, plan or act of self-harm/ suicide, or history thereof \n
        -> Any of the other priority conditions, chronic pain, or extreme emotional distress \n
        </item>
    </string-array>

    <string name="t">"> Always be respectful."\n"> Don’t judge people by their behaviours and appearance."\n"> Stay calm and patient."</string>
    <string name="s">"> Include the person (and with their consent, their carers and family) in all aspects of assessment and management as much as possible. This includes children, adolescents and older adults."</string>
    <string name="h">Show extra sensitivity with difﬁcult topics. Remind the person that what they tell you will remain conﬁdential. Acknowledge that it may have been difﬁcult for the person to disclose the information.</string>
    <string name="e">Use simple language. Be clear and concise. Use open-ended questions, summarizing and clarifying statements. Summarize and repeat key points. Allow the person to ask questions about the information provided.</string>
    <string name="r">"> Actively listen. Be empathic and sensitive."\n"> Allow the person to speak without interruption."\n"> If the history is unclear, be patient and ask for clariﬁcation."\n"> For children, use language that they can understand. For example, ask about their interests (toys, friends, school, etc.)."\n"> For adolescents, convey that you understand their feelings and situation."</string>
    <string name="i">"> Meet the person in a private space, if possible."\n ">Be welcoming and conduct introductions in a culturally appropriate manner."\n"> Maintain eye contact and use body language and facial expressions that facilitate trust."\n"> Explain that information discussed during the visit will be kept conﬁdential and will not be shared without prior permission."\n"> If carers are present, suggest to speak with the person alone (except for young children) and obtain consent to share clinical information."\n"> When interviewing a young woman, consider having another female staff member or carer present."\n</string>
    <string name="n">"COMMUNICATION TIP #1"\n" Create an environment that facilitates open communication"</string>
    <string name="g">"COMMUNICATION TIP #2"\n" Involve the person"</string>
    <string name="j">"COMMUNICATION TIP #3"\n" Start by listening"</string>
    <string name="a">"COMMUNICATION TIP #4" \n"Be friendly, respectful and nonjudgemental at all times"</string>
    <string name="m">"COMMUNICATION TIP #5"\n" Use good verbal communication skills"</string>
    <string name="o">"COMMUNICATION TIP #6"\n" Respond with sensitivity when people disclose difﬁcult experiences (e.g. sexual assault, violence or self-harm)"</string>
    <string name="donts">DONTs</string>
    <string name="dos">DOs</string>
    <string name="y">">Do not discriminate against people with MNS conditions."\n"> Do not ignore the priorities or wishes of people with MNS conditions."\n"> Do not make decisions for, on behalf of, or instead of the person with MNS conditions."\n"> Do not use overly technical language in explaining proposed treatment."</string>
    <string name="d">I. Use Effective Communication Skills</string>
    <string name="l">II. Promote Respect and Dignity</string>
    <string name="k">Persons with MNS conditions should be treated with respect and dignity in a culturally appropriate manner. As a health care provider, make every effort to respect and promote the will and preference of people with MNS conditions and support and engage them and their carers in the most inclusive way. Persons with MNS conditions are often more vulnerable to human rights violations. Therefore, it is essential that in the health care setting, providers promote the rights of people with MNS conditions in line with international human rights standards, including the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disability (CRPD)*.</string>
    <string name="u">"> Treat people with MNS conditions with respect and dignity."\n"> Protect the conﬁdentiality of people with MNS conditions."\n"> Ensure privacy in the clinical setting."\n"> Always provide access to information and explain the proposed treatment risks and beneﬁts in writing, if possible."\n"> Make sure the person provides consent to treatment."\n"> Promote autonomy and independent living in the community."\n"> Provide persons with MNS conditions with access to supported decision making options."</string>
    <string name="v">Using effective communication skills allows healthcare providers to deliver good quality care to adults, adolescents, and children with mental, neurological and substance use (MNS) conditions. Consider the following core communication skills and tips:</string>
    <string name="title_activity_essentail1">Essentail 1</string>
    <string name="title_activity_essential2">Essential 2</string>

    <string name="hello_blank_fragment">Hello blank fragment</string>
    <string name="history_taking">History Taking</string>
    <string name="ts">Treat existing comorbidities concurrently with the MNS disorder. Refer to/consult with specialists, if needed. Provide education on modiﬁable risk factors to prevent disease and encourage a healthy lifestyle. To support physical health of persons with MNS conditions, health care providers should: – Provide advice about the importance of physical activity and a healthy diet. – Educate people about harmful alcohol use. – Encourage cessation of tobacco and substance use. – Provide education about other risky behaviour (e.g. unprotected sex). – Conduct regular physical health checks and vaccinations. – Prepare people for developmental life changes, such as puberty and menopause, and provide the necessary support. – Discuss plans for pregnancy and contraception methods with women of childbearing age.</string>
    <string name="he" />
    <string name="ri">"1.Presenting Complaint"\n" Main symptom or reason that the person is seeking care."\n"> Ask when, why, and how it started."\n"> It is important at this stage to gather as much information as possible about the person’s symptoms and their situation."\n\n"2. Past MNS History"> Ask about similar problems in the past, any psychiatric hospitalizations or medications prescribed for MNS conditions, and any past suicide attempts."\n"> Explore tobacco, alcohol and substance use."\n\n"3. General Health History"\n"> Ask about physical health problems and medications."\n"> Obtain a list of current medications."\n"> Ask about allergies to medications"\n\n" 4.Family History of MNS Conditions"\n"> Explore possible family history of MNS conditions and ask if anyone had similar symptoms or has received treatment for a MNS condition."\n\n"5. Psychosocial History"\n"> Ask about current stressors, coping methods and social support."\n"> Ask about current socio-occupational functioning (how the person is functioning at home, work and in relationships)."\n"> Obtain basic information including where the person lives, level of education, work/employment history, marital status and number/ages of children, income, and household structure/living conditions."\n\n" For children and adolescents, ask about whether they have a carer, and the nature and quality of the relationship between them."</string>
    <string name="ja">Assessment of Physical Health</string>
    <string name="jaa">Conducting an assessment for MNS conditions involves the following steps. First, the presenting complaint is explored, then a history is obtained including asking about past MNS issues, general health problems, family MNS history, and psychosocial history. Observe the person (Mental Status Exam), establish a differential diagnosis, and identify the MNS condition. As part of the assessment, conduct a physical examination and obtain basic laboratory tests as needed. The assessment is conducted with informed consent of the person.</string>
    <string name="p">I. Assess Physical Health</string>
    <string name="zx">II. Conduct a MNS Assessment</string>
    <string name="pe">Management of Physical Health</string>
    <string name="ge">Persons with MNS disorders are at higher risk of premature mortality from preventable disease and therefore must always receive a physical health assessment as part of a comprehensive evaluation. Be sure to take a proper history, including both physical health and MNS history, followed by a physical health assessment to identify concurrent conditions and educate the person about preventive measures. These actions must always be undertaken with the person’s informed consent.</string>
    <string name="li">"> Take a detailed history and ask about risk factors."\n" Physical inactivity, inappropriate diet, tobacco, harmful alcohol and/or substance use, risky behaviour and chronic disease."\n"> Perform a physical examination."\n"> Consider a differential diagnosis."\n" Rule out physical conditions and underlying causes of MNS presentations by history, physical examination and basic laboratory tests as needed and available."\n"> Identify comorbidities."\n" Often, a person may have more than one MNS condition at the same time. It is important to assess and manage this when it occurs."</string>
    <string name="ml">"> Treat existing comorbidities concurrently with the MNS disorder. Refer to/consult with specialists, if needed."\n"> Provide education on modiﬁable risk factors to prevent disease and encourage a healthy lifestyle."\n">To support physical health of persons with MNS conditions, health care providers should:"\n" – Provide advice about the importance of physical activity and a healthy diet."\n" – Educate people about harmful alcohol use. "\n"– Encourage cessation of tobacco and substance use."\n" – Provide education about other risky behaviour (e.g. unprotected sex)."\n" – Conduct regular physical health checks and vaccinations."\n" – Prepare people for developmental life changes, such as puberty and menopause, and provide the necessary support."\n "– Discuss plans for pregnancy and contraception methods with women of childbearing age"</string>
    <string name="title_activity_essen">Essential Care</string>
    <string name="title_activity_essen_b">Essential care</string>
    <string name="we">5.Ensure that appropriate plan for follow-up is in place.</string>
    <string name="are">6.Work together with carer and families in supporting the person with the MNS disorder</string>
    <string name="_te">"1. Physical Examination"\n"> Conduct a targeted physical examination guided by the information found during the MNS assessment."</string>
    <string name="ui">1.Develop a treatment plan in collaboration with the person and their carer.</string>
    <string name="_2_always_offer_psychosocial_interventions_for_the_person_and_their_carers">2 Always offer psychosocial interventions for the person and their carers.</string>
    <string name="ni">"2.Mental Status Examination (MSE)*"\n"> Ask about and observe the person’s Appearance and Behaviour, Mood and Affect, Content of Thought, any Perceptual disturbances and Cognition. See symptom based Master Chart (MC) for details."</string>
    <string name="lo">3. Treat the MNS disorder using pharmacological interventions when indicated.</string>
    <string name="po">"3.Differential Diagnosis "\n">Consider the differential diagnosis and rule out conditions that have similar presenting symptoms."</string>
    <string name="ki">4. Refer to specialists or hospital when indicated and available</string>
    <string name="ju">"4.Basic Laboratory Tests"\n"> Request laboratory tests when indicated and possible, especially to rule out physical causes."</string>
    <string name="ln">7. Foster strong links with employment, education, social services (including housing) and other relevant sectors.</string>
    <string name="jh">8. Modify treatment plans for special populations.</string>
    <string name="qa">ASSESSMENT FOR MNS CONDITIONS</string>
    <string name="vd">"CLINICAL TIP:"\n" Written treatment plan should cover:"\n" – Pharmacological interventions (if any)"\n" – Psychosocial interventions"\n" – Referrals"\n" – Follow-up plan"\n" – Management of any concurrent physical and/or other MNS conditions"</string>
    <string name="f">III. Manage MNS Conditions</string>
    <string name="mj">MANAGEMENT STEPS FOR MNS CONDITIONS</string>
    <string name="hg">Once the assessment is conducted, follow the management algorithm in mhGAP-IG to manage the MNS disorder. Key steps in management are found in the box below.</string>
    <string name="cs">Suspect a priority MNS condition and go to the relevant module(s) for assessment</string>
    <string name="essential_care">Essential Care</string>
    <string name="a_general_principles">A. GENERAL PRINCIPLES</string>
    <string name="b_essentials_of_mental_health_clinical_practice">B. ESSENTIALS OF MENTAL HEALTH CLINICAL PRACTICE</string>
    <string name="hu">"Identify the MNS Condition"\n"> Identify the MNS condition using the appropriate module(s)."\n "> Assess for other MNS symptoms and priority conditions (see Master Chart)." \n"> Follow the appropriate management algorithm and treatment protocols."</string>
    <string name="title_activity_depression">Depression</string>
    <string name="dep">
        People with depression experience a range of symptoms
including persistent depressed mood or loss of interest and
pleasure for at least 2 weeks.\n\n
People with depression as described in this module have
considerable difficulty with daily functioning in personal, family,
social, educational, occupational or other areas.\n\n
Many people with depression also suffer from anxiety symptoms
and medically unexplained somatic symptoms.\n\nDepression commonly occurs alongside other MNS conditions as
well as physical conditions.\n\n
The management of symptoms not fully meeting the criteria
for depression is covered within the module on Other Significant
Mental Health Complaints. Go to » OTH.
    </string>


    <string name="psy">
        \n\nThe psychoses module covers management of two severe mental
health conditions, psychosis and bipolar disorder. People with
psychosis or bipolar disorder are at high risk of exposure to stigma,
discrimination and violation of their right to live with dignity.\n\n
Psychosis is characterised by distorted thoughts and perceptions,
as well as disturbed emotions and behaviours. Incoherent or irrelevant
speech may also be present. Symptoms such as hallucinations –
hearing voices, or seeing things that are not there; delusions –
fixed, false beliefs; severe abnormalities of behaviour – disorganised
behaviour, agitation, excitement, inactivity, or hyperactivity;
disturbances of emotion – marked apathy, or disconnect between
reported emotion and observed affect, such as facial expression
and body language, may also be detected.\n\n
Bipolar disorder is characterized by episodes in which the person’s
mood and activity levels are significantly disturbed. This disturbance
consists on some occasions of an elevation of mood and increased
energy and activity (mania), and on others of a lowering of mood
and decreased energy and activity (depression). Characteristically,
recovery is complete between episodes. People who experience only
manic episodes are also classified as having bipolar disorder.
33</string>
    <string name="epi">Epilepsy is a chronic noncommunicable disorder of the brain,
characterized by recurrent unprovoked seizures. Epilepsy is one
of the most common neurological disorders and with proper
treatment, can be well controlled in the majority of people.\n\n
Epilepsy has many causes. It may be genetic. Epilepsy may occur
in people who have a past history of birth trauma, brain injury
(including head trauma and strokes), or brain infections. In some
people, no cause may be identified.\n\n
Seizures are caused by abnormal electrical activity in the brain and
are of two types: convulsive and non-convulsive. Non-convulsive
epilepsy has features such as change in mental status while convulsive
epilepsy has features such as sudden abnormal movements,
including stiffening and shaking of the body. The latter is associated
with greater stigma and higher morbidity and mortality. This module
covers only convulsive epilepsy.</string>

    <string name="cmh">DEVELOPMENTAL DISORDER is an umbrella term covering
disorders such as intellectual disability as well as autism spectrum
disorders. These disorders usually have a childhood onset, impairment
or delay in functions related to central nervous system maturation,
and a steady course rather than the remissions and relapses
that tend to characterize many other mental disorders.\n\n
BEHAVIOURAL DISORDERS is an umbrella term that includes
specific disorders such as attention deficit hyperactivity disorder
(ADHD) and conduct disorders. Behavioural symptoms of varying
levels of severity are very common in the general population. Only
children and adolescents with a moderate to severe degree of psychological,
social, educational or occupational impairment in multiple
settings should be diagnosed as having behavioural disorders.\n\n
EMOTIONAL DISORDERS are among the leading mental healthrelated
causes of the global burden of disease in young people.
Emotional disorders are characterized by increased levels of anxiety,
depression, fear, and somatic symptoms.
</string>
    <string name="dem">Dementia is a chronic and progressive syndrome due to changes
in the brain. Although it can occur at any age, it is more common
in older people. Dementia is a significant cause of disability and
dependency among older people worldwide; it has a physical,
psychological, social, and economic impact on carers, families,
and society at large.\n\n
The conditions that cause dementia produce changes in a person’s
mental ability, personality, and behaviour. People with dementia
commonly experience problems with memory and the skills needed
to carry out everyday activities. Dementia is not part of normal
ageing. Alzheimer’s disease is the most common cause, however,
dementia can be caused by a variety of diseases and injuries to the
brain. People with dementia often present with forgetfulness or
feeling depressed. Other common symptoms include deterioration
in emotional control, social behaviour, or motivation. People with
dementia may be totally unaware of these changes and may not
seek help. Family members may notice memory problems, changes
in personality or behaviour, confusion, wandering, or incontinence.

 </string>

    <string name="sub">Disorders due to substance use include both drug and alcohol
use disorders and certain conditions including acute intoxication,
overdose and withdrawal.\n\n
ACUTE INTOXICATION is a transient condition following intake of
a psychoactive substance resulting in disturbances of consciousness,
cognition, perception, affect, or behaviour.\n\n
OVERDOSE is the use of any drug in such an amount that acute
adverse physical or mental effects are produced.\n\n
WITHDRAWAL is the experience of a set of unpleasant symptoms
following the abrupt cessation or reduction in dose of a psychoactive
substance; it has been consumed in high enough doses and for a
long enough duration for the person to be physically or mentally
dependent on it.\n\n
HARMFUL USE is a pattern of psychoactive substance use
that damages health. This damage may be physical, e.g. liver
disease, or mental.
</string>

    <string name="sui">Suicide is the act of deliberately killing oneself. Self-harm is a
broader term referring to intentional self-inflicted poisoning or
injury, which may or may not have a fatal intent or outcome.
Any person over 10 years of age experiencing any of the following
conditions should be asked about thoughts or plans of self-harm
in the last month, and about acts of self-harm in the last year:\n\n
» Any of the priority MNS conditions. See Master Chart ( MC)\n
» Chronic pain\n
» Acute emotional distress\n\n
        CLINICAL TIP:\n
Asking about self-harm does NOT provoke acts of self-harm. It often reduces
anxiety associated with thoughts or acts of self-harm and helps the person feel
understood. However, try to establish a relationship with the person before asking
questions about self-harm. Ask the person to explain their reasons for harming
themselves.
    </string>

    <string-array name="glossary">
        <item>Activities of daily living (ADLs)</item>
        <item>Agitation</item>
        <item>Agranulocytosis</item>
        <item>Akathisia</item>
        <item>Akinesia</item>
        <item>Altered mental status</item>
        <item>Alzheimers disease</item>
        <item>Anticholinergic sideeffects</item>
        <item>Aplastic anaemia</item>
        <item>Ataxi</item>
        <item>Autism spectrum disorders</item>
        <item>Autonomy</item>
        <item>Behavioural activation </item>
        <item>Bereavement</item>
        <item>Cerebrovascular accident</item>
        <item>Cognitive</item>
        <item>Cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT)</item>
        <item>Comborbid,comorbidity</item>
        <item>Conﬁdentiality</item>
        <item>Confusion,  confusional state</item>
        <item>Contingency management therapy</item>
        <item>Convulsion, convulsive movement</item>
        <item>Delirium</item>
        <item>Delusion</item>
        <item>Detoxiﬁcation</item>
        <item>Disability</item>
        <item>Disinhibited behaviour, disinhibition</item>
        <item>Disorganized / disordered thinking</item>
        <item>Disorganized behaviour</item>
        <item>Distractibility</item>
        <item>Dystonia</item>
        <item>Eclampsia</item>
        <item>Elevated mood</item>
        <item>Extrapyramidal  side-effects / symptoms (EPS)</item>
        <item>Fetal alcohol syndrome </item>
        <item>Fits</item>
        <item>Focal deﬁcits</item>
        <item>Hallucination</item>
        <item>Hepatic encephalopathy</item>
        <item>Herbal products </item>
        <item>Hyperarousal</item>
        <item>Hypersensitivity reaction</item>
        <item>Idiosyncratic reaction </item>
        <item>Informed consent </item>
        <item>Interpersonal therapy (IPT)</item>
        <item>irritability,irritable mood</item>
        <item>Maculopapular rash</item>
        <item>Meningeal irritation </item>
        <item>Meningitis</item>
        <item>Motivational enhancement therapy</item>
        <item>Motor twitching </item>
        <item>Myasthenia gravis </item>
        <item>Neonatal abstinence syndrome</item>
        <item>Neuroinfection</item>
        <item>Neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS)</item>
        <item>Occupational therapy </item>
        <item>Oppositional behaviour </item>
        <item>Orthostatic hypotension</item>
        <item>Parent Skills Training </item>
        <item>Phaeochromocytoma</item>
        <item>Polyneuropathy</item>
        <item>Polytherapy</item>
        <item>Porphyria</item>
        <item>Privacy</item>
        <item>Problem-solving counselling</item>
        <item>Pruritus</item>
        <item>Pseudodementia</item>
        <item>Psychoeducation</item>
        <item>QT prolongation</item>
        <item>Racing thoughts</item>
        <item>Relapse</item>
        <item>Relaxation training</item>
        <item>Respiratory depression </item>
        <item>Respite care </item>
        <item>Rigidity</item>
        <item>Saving group </item>
        <item>Seizure</item>
        <item>Self-harm </item>
        <item>Serotonin syndrome </item>
        <item>Slurred speech</item>
        <item>Social network</item>
        <item>Social withdrawal</item>
        <item>Spider naevus </item>
        <item>Spinal abscess </item>
        <item>Status epilepticus </item>
        <item>Stevens-Johnson syndrome</item>
        <item>Stigma</item>
        <item>Stroke</item>
        <item>Sucidal thoughts/ideation</item>
        <item>Tardive dyskinesia </item>
        <item>Temper tantrum </item>
        <item>Thrombocytopenia</item>
        <item>Toxic epidermal necrolysis</item>
        <item>Traditional Healing </item>
        <item>Transient ischaemic attack (TIA)</item>
        <item>Tremor</item>
        <item>Vitamin K deﬁciency disease of the newborn</item>
        <item>Wandering</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="glossary_meaning">
        <item>A concept of functioning – activities of daily living are basic activities that are necessary for independent living, including eating, bathing and toileting. This concept has several assessment tools to determine an individual’s ability to perform the activity with or without assistance.</item>
        <item> Marked restlessness and excessive motor activity, accompanied by anxiety. </item>
        <item> A blood disorder in which there is an absence of granulocytes  (a type of white blood cell). It is an acute condition involving a severe and dangerous leukopenia, also known as drug-induced secondary agranulocytosis. </item>
        <item> A subjective sense of restlessness, often accompanied by observed excessive movements (e.g. ﬁdgety movements of the legs, rocking from foot to foot, pacing, inability to sit or stand still). </item>
        <item> The absence or lack of voluntary movement. A state of difﬁculty in initiating movements or changing from one motor pattern to another that is associated with Parkinson’s disease. </item>
        <item> A changed level of awareness or mental state that falls short of unconsciousness which is often induced by substance intake or other mental or neurological conditions. Examples include confusion and disorientation. See delirium and confusional state. </item>
        <item> A primary degenerative cerebral disease of unknown etiology in  the majority of cases with characteristic neuropathological and neurochemical features. The disorder is usually insidious in onset and develops slowly but steadily over a period of several years. </item>
        <item>Anticholinergic medicines block the effects of acetylcholine at muscarinic receptors. Anticholinergic effects include dryness of the mouth, urinary frequency or retention, palpitations and sinus tachycardia. </item>
        <item>A disease characterized by the inability of  blood stem cells to generate new mature cells. This disease is also characterised by low levels of red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets. This disease may present with pallor, fatigue, dizziness, increased risk of infection or increased bruising or bleeding.
Ataxia </item>
        <item>Failure of muscular coordination. People with ataxiz have problems with coordination because parts of the nervous system that control movement and balance are affected. Ataxia may affect the ﬁngers, hands, arms, legs, body, speech, and eye movements.</item>
        <item>An umbrella term that covers conditions such as autism, childhood disintegration disorder and Asperger’s syndrome. </item>
        <item>The perceived ability to control, cope with and make personal decisions about how one lives on a daily basis, according to one’s own rules and preferences. </item>
        <item>Psychological treatment that focuses on improving mood by engaging again in activities that are task-oriented and used to be enjoyable, in spite of current low mood. It may be used as a stand-alone treatment, and it is also a component of cognitive behavioural therapy. </item>
        <item> A process of loss, grief and recovery, usually associated with death.</item>
        <item>A sudden disturbance of cerebral function attributable to vascular disease, principally thrombosis, haemorrhage, or embolism. See stroke.</item>
        <item> Mental processes associated with thinking. These include reasoning, remembering, judgement, problem-solving and planning. </item>
        <item>Psychological treatment that combines cognitive components (aimed at thinking differently, for example through identifying and challenging unrealistic negative thoughts) and behavioural components (aimed at doing things differently, for example by helping the person to do more rewarding activities). </item>
        <item> Describing diseases or disorders that exist simultaneously. </item>
        <item> Privacy in the context of privileged communication (such as patient doctor consultations) and medical records is safeguarded. </item>
        <item>A state of impaired consciousness associated with acute or chronic cerebral organic disease. Clinically it is characterized by disorientation, slowness of mental processes with scanty association of ideas, apathy, lack of initiative, fatigue, and poor attention. In mild confusional states, rational responses and behaviour may be provoked by examination but more severe degrees of the disorder render the individual unable to retain contact with the environment.</item>
        <item>A structured method of rewarding certain desired behaviours, such as attending treatment and avoiding harmful substance use. Rewards for desired behaviours are reduced over time as the natural rewards become established. </item>
        <item>Clinical or subclinical disturbances of cortical function due to a sudden, abnormal, excessive, and disorganized discharge of brain cells (see seizure). Clinical manifestations include abnormal motor, sensory and psychic phenomena. </item>
        <item>Transient ﬂuctuating mental state characterized by disturbed attention (i.e., reduced ability to direct, focus, sustain, and shift attention) and awareness (i.e., reduced orientation to the environment) that develops over a short period of time and tends to ﬂuctuate during the course of a day. It is accompanied by (other) disturbances of perception, memory, thinking, emotions or psychomotor functions. It may result from acute organic causes such as infections, medication, metabolic abnormalities, substance intoxication or substance withdrawal. </item>
        <item> Fixed belief that is contrary to available evidence. It cannot be changed by rational argument and is not accepted by other members of the person’s culture or subculture (i.e., it is not an aspect of religious faith). </item>
        <item> The process by which an individual is withdrawn from the effects of a psychoactive substance. Also referring to a clinical procedure, the withdrawal process is carried out in a safe and effective manner, such that withdrawal symptoms are minimized. </item>
        <item>Any restriction or lack (resulting from an impairment) of ability to perform an activity in the manner, or within the range, considered to be normal for a human being. The term disability reﬂects the consequences of impairment in terms of functional performance and activity by the individual. </item>
        <item>Lack of restraint manifested in disregard for social conventions, impulsivity and poor risk assessment. It can affect motor, emotional, cognitive and perceptual aspects of a person’s functioning.</item>
        <item>Lack of restraint manifested in disregard for social conventions, impulsivity and poor risk assessment. It can affect motor, emotional, cognitive and perceptual aspects of a person’s functioning.</item>
        <item>Behaviour including posture, gait, and other activity that is unpredictable or not goal-directed (e.g., shouting at strangers on the street).</item>
        <item> Difﬁculty concentrating and focusing on tasks; attention is easily diverted by extraneous stimuli.</item>
        <item>Sustained muscle contraction or involuntary movements that can lead to ﬁxed abnormal postures. See tardive dyskinesia. </item>
        <item> Any condition affecting pregnant women, characterized by seizure or convulsions newly arising in pregnancy. The condition is often associated with pregnancy-induced hypertension, convulsions, seizure, anxiety, epigastric pain, severe headache, blurred vision, proteinuria, and oedema that may occur during pregnancy, labour, or the puerperium. </item>
        <item> A positive mood state typically characterized by increased energy and self-esteem which may be out of proportion to the individuals life circumstances. </item>
        <item>Abnormalities in muscle movement, mostly caused by antipsychotic medication. These include muscle tremors, stiffness, spasms and/or akathisia.</item>
        <item> Counselling that entails multiple (usually more than six) planned sessions over a period of months. It should be delivered to individual families or groups of families, and should include the person living with mental illness, if feasible. It has supportive and educational or treatment functions. It often includes negotiated problem-solving or crisis management work. </item>
        <item> Fetal alcohol syndrome is a malformation syndrome caused by maternal consumption of alcohol during pregnancy. It is characterized by prenatal and/or postnatal growth deﬁciency and a unique cluster of minor facial anomalies that presents across all ethnic groups, is identiﬁable at birth, and does not diminish with age. Affected children present severe central nervous system abnormalities including: microcephaly, cognitive and behavioural impairment (intellectual disability, deﬁcit in general cognition, learning and language, executive function, visual-spatial processing, memory, and attention). </item>
        <item>Colloquial term for convulsions. See convulsion</item>
        <item>Neurological signs that are observable bodily phenomena or responses suggestive of the localization of a relatively circumscribed lesion of the nervous system.</item>
        <item>False perception of reality: seeing, hearing, feeling, smelling or tasting things that are not real. </item>
        <item>Abnormal mental state including drowsiness, confusion or coma caused by liver dysfunction.</item>
        <item>A range of folk medicines, many of them empirically discovered hundreds of years ago to be effective, derived from or consisting of portions of plants. In many cultures, knowledge about the efﬁcacy of herbal remedies is carefully preserved and handed on by oral tradition from one generation to the next. </item>
        <item> Intense and prolonged autonomic discharge accompanied by a state of frozen watchfulness and alertness to environmental stimuli. Such responses are seen most frequently in post-traumatic stress disorders and often associated with substance use or withdrawal.</item>
        <item>Hypersensitivity reactions are the adverse effects of pharmaceutical formulations (including active drugs and excipients) that clinically resemble allergy. It belongs to type B adverse drug reactions, which are deﬁned by the WHO as the dose-independent, unpredictable, noxious, and unintended response to a medicine taken at a dose normally used in humans. It covers many different clinical phenotypes with variable onset and severity. </item>
        <item> Individual, unpredictable, and non-dose-dependent response to any substance: drowsiness or euphoria, ﬂushing, carpopedal spasms, apnoea, etc.</item>
        <item>The process by which the health care provider discloses appropriate information to a person who can then make a  voluntary choice to accept or refuse treatment. informed consent includes a discussion of the following elements: the nature of the decision/procedure; reasonable alternatives to the proposed intervention; the relevant risks, beneﬁts, and uncertainties related to each alternative; assessment of the person’s understanding, and the acceptance of the intervention by the person. </item>
        <item>Psychological treatment that focuses on the link between depressive symptoms and interpersonal problems, especially those involving grief, disputes, life changes and social isolation. It is also known as Interpersonal Psychotherapy. Irritability</item>
        <item>A mood state characterized by being easily annoyed and provoked to anger, out of proportion to the circumstances</item>
        <item>A rash that consists of both macules (ﬂat (impalpable), circumscribed areas of skin or areas of altered skin colour (e.g. freckles)) and papules (small raised spots on the skin, often dome-shaped and less than 5 mm in diameter). </item>
        <item> Irritation of the layers of tissue that cover the brain and spinal cord, usually caused by an infection. </item>
        <item> A disease of the meninges (the membranes covering the brain and spinal cord) usually caused by an infection with a bacterial, viral, fungal, or parasitic source. </item>
        <item>A structured therapy (lasting 4 or less sessions) to help people with substance use disorders. It involves an approach to motivate change by using motivational interviewing techniques i.e. engaging the person in a discussion about their substance use including perceived beneﬁts and harms in relation to the persons own values, avoiding arguing with the person if there is resistance, encouraging the person to decide for themselves what their goal may be. </item>
        <item>See convulsion. </item>
        <item>A disorder of neuromuscular transmission characterized by fatigable weakness of cranial and skeletal muscles. Clinical manifestations may include ﬂuctuating diplopia and ptosis, and fatigable weakness of facial, bulbar, respiratory, and proximal limb muscles. </item>
        <item>Intrauterine exposure to addictive drugs can lead to neonatal withdrawal symptoms. Withdrawal symptoms are usually neurological, preventing normal autonomic function. The clinical presentation of drug withdrawal is variable and dependent on several factors, such as, the type and dose of drug used, and rate of metabolism and excretion of the mother and infant. </item>
        <item>Infection involving the brain and/or spinal cord. </item>
        <item>A rare but life-threatening condition caused by antipsychotic medications, which is characterised by fever, delirium, muscular rigidity and high blood pressure.</item>
        <item>Therapy designed to help individuals improve their independence in daily living activities through rehabilitation, exercises and the use of assistive devices. In addition, such therapy provides activities to promote growth, self-fulﬁlment and self-esteem. </item>
        <item> Markedly deﬁant, disobedient, provocative or spiteful behaviour that may be manifest in prevailing, persistent angry or irritable mood, often accompanied by severe temper outbursts or in headstrong, argumentative and deﬁant behaviour. </item>
        <item>Sudden drop of blood pressure that can occur when one changes position from lying to sitting or standing up, usually leading to feelings of light-headedness or dizziness. It is not life-threatening. </item>
        <item> A family of treatment programs that aims to change parenting behaviours and strengthen conﬁdence in adoption of effective parenting strategies. It involves teaching parents emotional communication and positive parent-child interaction skills, and positive reinforcement methods to improve children/adolescent’s behaviour and functioning. </item>
        <item> A neuroendocrine tumour of the medulla of the adrenal glands  causing symptoms (mainly headaches, palpitations and excess sweating) and signs (mainly hypertension, weight loss and diabetes) reﬂecting the effects of epinephrine and norepinephrine on alpha- and beta-adrenergic receptors. </item>
        <item> Disorder and functional disturbance of the peripheral nerves. This may be manifest as numbness of the extremities, paraesthesia ("pins and needles" sensations), weakness of the limbs, or wasting of the muscles and loss of deep tendon reﬂexes. </item>
        <item> Provision of more than one medicine at the same time for the same condition. </item>
        <item> Porphyrias constitute a group of diseases characterized by intermittent neuro-visceral manifestations, cutaneous lesions or by the combination of both. Clinical signs of the disease usually appear in adulthood, but some porphyrias affect children. Direct or indirect neurotoxicity may cause neurological manifestations.</item>
        <item>The state of being free from unsanctioned intrusion. For example, personal privacy in daily living activities (e.g. for clients in residential facilities) or conﬁdential health records. </item>
        <item>Psychological treatment that involves the systematic use of problem iden- tiﬁcation and problem-solving techniques over a number of sessions.</item>
        <item>Itching, an intense sensation that produces the urge to rub or scratch the skin to obtain relief.</item>
        <item> A disorder resembling dementia but not due to organic brain disease and potentially reversible by treatment; can manifest as symptoms of depression in some older adults. </item>
        <item>The process of teaching people with MNS disorders and their carers/ family members about the nature of the illness, including its likely causes, progression, consequences, prognosis, treatment and alternatives. </item>
        <item> A potential medication induced side-effect of ventricular myocardial repolarization characterized by a prolonged QT interval on the electrocardiogram (ECG) that can lead to symptomatic ventricular arrhythmias and an increased risk of sudden cardiac death.</item>
        <item>Rapid thought pattern with tangential movement from one idea to the next often associated with mania or other mental illnesses.</item>
        <item>A return to drinking or other drug use after a period, of abstinence, often accompanied by reinstatement of dependence symptoms. The term is also used to indicate return of symptoms of MNS disorder after a period of recovery. </item>
        <item>Involves training in techniques such as breathing exercises to elicit the relaxation response. </item>
        <item>Inadequate slow breathing rate, resulting in insufﬁcient oxygen. Common causes include brain injury and intoxication (e.g. due to benzodiazepines). </item>
        <item> Provision of temporary health-care facilities to a person normally cared for at home. </item>
        <item>Resistance to the passive movement of a limb that persists throughout its range. It is a symptom of parkinsonism. </item>
        <item> A saving activity in which the poor can accumulate a large amount of money quickly by pooling their savings in a common fund which can then be used by the group or a member of the group for productive investment.</item>
        <item>Episode of brain malfunction due to disturbances of cortical function resulting in sudden, abnormal, excessive, and disorganized discharge of brain cells. Clinical manifestations include abnormal motor, sensory and psychic phenomena. </item>
        <item> Intentional self-inﬂicted poisoning or injury to oneself, which may or may not have a fatal intent or outcome.</item>
        <item>Characterised by an excess of serotonin in the central nervous system, associated with the use of various agents, including selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs). Serotonin syndrome may result in muscle rigidity, myoclonus, agitation, confusion, hyperthermia,  hyperreﬂexia as well as dysautonomic symptoms, with a risk of  shock with low peripheral vascular resistance, seizures, coma, rhabdomyolysis and/or disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC). </item>
        <item>Speech with indistinctive pronunciation. </item>
        <item> A construct of analytical sociology referring to the characteristics of the social linkages among people as a means of understanding their behaviour, rather than focusing on the attributes of individuals. </item>
        <item> Inability of a person to engage in age appropriate activities or interactions with his or her peers or family members.</item>
        <item> A cluster of minute red blood vessels visible under the skin, occurring typically during pregnancy or as a symptom of certain diseases (e.g. cirrhosis or acne rosacea). </item>
        <item>A condition of the spinal cord, caused by an infection with a bacterial, viral, or fungal source. This condition is characterized by a focal accumu- lation of purulent material within the spinal cord. This condition may present with fever, back pain and neurological deﬁcits. Transmission is through haematogenous spread of the infectious agent. </item>
        <item>Deﬁned as 5 min or more of continuous clinical and/or electrographic seizure activity or recurrent seizure activity without recovery (returning to baseline) between seizures; it can be convulsive or non-convulsive. </item>
        <item>Life-threatening skin condition characterized by painful skin peeling, ulcers, blisters and crusting of mucocutaneous tissues such as mouth, lips, throat, tongue, eyes and genitals, sometimes associated with fever. It is most often caused by severe reaction to medications, especially antiepileptic medicines. </item>
        <item>A distinguishing mark establishing a demarcation between the stigmatized person and others attributing negative characteristics to this person. The stigma attached to mental illness often leads to social exclusion and discrimination and creates an additional burden for the affected individual. </item>
        <item>See cerebrovascular accident (CVA).</item>
        <item>Thoughts, idead, or ruminations about the possibility of ending ones life, ranging from thinking that one would be better off dead to formulation of elaborate plans.</item>
        <item>This is dystonia characterized by twisting and sustained muscle spasms that affect regions of the head, neck, and occasionally, the back. It may not improve after stopping the antipsychotic medicine. </item>
        <item> An emotional outburst from a child or those in emotional distress. </item>
        <item> Abnormally low number of platelets in the blood. This disease may present with increased bruising or haemorrhaging. Conﬁrmation is by identiﬁcation of decreased platelet count in a blood sample. </item>
        <item>Life-threatening skin peeling that is usually caused by a reaction to a medicine or infection. It is similar to but more severe than StevensJohnson syndrome. </item>
        <item> A system of treatment modalities based on indigenous knowledge of different cultures pertaining to healing. </item>
        <item>A transient episode of acute focal neurological dysfunction caused by focal ischemia of the brain or retina, without demonstrated acute infarction in the clinically relevant area of the brain. Symptoms should resolve completely within 24 hours. </item>
        <item>Trembling or shaking movements, usually of the ﬁngers, that is an involuntary oscillation of a body part. </item>
        <item>Lack of vitamin K can cause severe bleeding in newborn babies usually immediately after birth but sometimes up to 6 months of age. Bleeding may be cutaneous, gastro-intestinal, intracranial or mucosal. Maternal intake of antiepiletic medicines is one of its causes.</item>
        <item> People living with dementia feel the urge to walk about and in some cases leave their homes. They can often experience problems with orientation, which may cause them to become lost.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string name="oth">This module aims to provide basic guidance on management
of a range of mental health complaints not covered elsewhere in
this guide. Some of these complaints may be similar to depression,
but upon closer examination are distinct from the conditions
covered in this guide.\n\n
    Other mental health complaints are considered significant
when they impair daily functioning or when the person seeks
help for them. Other mental health complaints can be due
to stress.\n\n
    This module should not be considered for people who meet the criteria for any of the mhGAP priority conditions (except self-harm).\n
This module should only be used after explicitly ruling out depression.\n
This module should be used when helping adults. In case the person is a child or adolescent, go to » CMH.</string>
    <string name="title_activity_depression3">depression3</string>
    <string name="section_format">Hello World from section: %1$d</string>
    <string name="help1">The mhGAP-IG is a model guide and it is essential that it is
adapted to the unique national or local situation. Users may
select a subset of the priority conditions or interventions to
adapt and implement, depending on the context.</string>

    <string name="help2">The mhGAP App begins with “Essential Care and Practice”,
        a set of good clinical practices and general guidelines for
        interactions of health care providers with people seeking
        mental health care. All users of the mhGAP-IG should
        familiarize themselves with these principles and should
        follow them as far as possible.\n\n

        The mhGAP App includes a “Master Chart”, which provides
information on common presentations of the priority
conditions. This guides the clinician to the relevant modules.
The most serious conditions should be managed first.
mhGAP-IG 2.0 has a new addition to the Master Chart –
Emergency Presentations of Priority MNS Conditions.
This section has been added to help identify emergency
situations and direction to management guidelines.\n\n
The modules, organized by individual priority conditions, are
a tool for clinical decision-making and management. Each
module is in a different colour to allow easy differentiation.
There is an introduction at the beginning of each module
that explains which condition(s) the module covers and a
quick overview describing key assessment and management
steps.
 </string>
    <string name="jam">Mental, neurological and substance use (MNS) disorders are highly prevalent,
accounting for a large burden of disease and disability globally. There remains a
wide gap between available health systems capacity and resources, what is urgently
needed, and what is available to reduce the burden.\n\n
    The key objectives of mhGAP
are to reinforce the commitment of governments, international organizations and other
stakeholders to increase the allocation of financial and human resources for care
of MNS disorders and to achieve much higher coverage with key interventions in lowand
middle-income countries.</string>
    <string name="help3">The Assessment section is presented in a framework of
flowcharts with multiple clinical assessment points. Each
module starts with common presentations of the suspected
condition, from which there are a series of clinical assessment
questions one should move down answering yes or no,
which directs the user to move on for further instructions to
reach a final clinical assessment. It is important that users of
the mhGAP start at the top of the assessment and move
through all the decision points to develop a comprehensive
clinical assessment and management plan.\n\n
The Management section consists of intervention details
which provide information on how to manage the specific
conditions that have been assessed. This includes more
technical psychosocial and pharmacological interventions
when appropriate.\n\n
The Follow-up section provides detailed information on
how to continue the clinical relationship and detailed
instructions for follow-up management.\n\n
The mhGAP uses a series of symbols to highlight
certain aspects within the modules. A list of the symbols
and their explanation is given on the following page.
Throughout the modules, important points are also
highlighted as key clinical tips.\n\n
Also included is a module on Implementation of mhGAP-IG,
which provides summary steps on how to implement
mhGAP.\n\n
At the end of the guide, a glossary of terms used in
mhGAP is provided.</string>
    <string name="title_activity_dep_assesment">Dep_assesment</string>
    <string name="begin_test">Begin test</string>
    <string name="dep_protocol2.1">Depression is a very common condition that can happen
to anybody.\n\n
The occurrence of depression does not mean that the person
is weak or lazy.\n\n
Negative attitudes of others (e.g. “You should be stronger”,
“Pull yourself together”) may be because depression is
not a visible condition, unlike a fracture or a wound. There
is also the misconception that people with depression can
easily control their symptoms by sheer willpower.\n\n
People with depression tend to have unrealistically negative
opinions about themselves, their life and their future. Their
current situation may be very difficult, but depression can
cause unjustified thoughts of hopelessness and
worthlessness. These views are likely to improve once the
depression improves.\n\n
Thoughts of self-harm or suicide are common. If they
notice these thoughts, they should not act on them, but
should tell a trusted person and come back for help
immediately.</string>
    <string name="dep_protocol2.2">Assess for and try to reduce stressors. (Go to » ECP)\n\n
Reactivate the person’s previous social network. Identify prior
social activities that, if started again, may potentially provide
direct or indirect psychosocial support, e.g. family gatherings,
visiting neighbours, and community activities.</string>

    <string name="dep_protocol2.3">Even if it is difficult, encourage the person to try to do as
many of the following as possible:\n\n
– Try to start again (or continue) activities that were
previously pleasurable.\n
– Try to maintain regular sleeping and waking times.\n
– Try to be as physically active as possible.\n
– Try to eat regularly despite changes in appetite.\n
– Try to spend time with trusted friends and family.\n
– Try to participate in community and other social activities
as much as possible.\n\n
Explain to the person and carer that these activities can
all help improve mood.</string>
    <string name="dep_protocol2.4">2.4 If available, consider referral for one of the
following brief psychological treatments:
interpersonal therapy (IPT), cognitive behavioural
therapy (CBT), behaviour activation and problem solving
counselling.</string>
    <string name="dep_protocol2.5">2.5 Consider antidepressants.</string>
    <string name="dep_protocol2.6"> DO NOT manage the symptoms with ineffective
treatments, e.g. vitamin injections.\nOffer regular follow-up.</string>

    <string name="dep_protocol">Discuss with the person and decide together whether to
prescribe antidepressants. Explain that:\n\n
– Antidepressants are not addictive.\n
– It is very important to take the medication every day as
prescribed.\n
– Some side effects may be experienced within the first few
days but they usually resolve.\n
– It usually takes several weeks before improvements in
mood, interest or energy is noticed.\n\n
Consider the person’s age, concurrent medical conditions,
and drug side-effect profile.\n\n
Start with only one medication at the lowest starting dose.\n\n
Antidepressant medications usually need to be continued
for at least 9-12 months after the resolution of symptoms.\n\n
Medications should never be stopped just because the
person experiences some improvement. Educate the person
on the recommended time frame to take medications.</string>
    <string name="caution1">If the person develops a manic episode, stop the antidepressant
immediately; it may trigger a manic episode
in untreated bipolar disorder.\n\n
Do not combine with other antidepressants, as this may
cause serotonin syndrome.\n\n
Antidepressants may increase suicidal</string>
    <string name="caution2">If symptoms persist or worsen despite psychosocial interventions,
consider fluoxetine (but no other selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) or tricyclic antidepressant (TCA).\n\n
If fluoxetine is prescribed, ask the adolescent to return weekly,
for the first 4 weeks, to monitor thoughts or plans of suicide.</string>
    <string name="caution3">Avoid antidepressants, if possible.\n\n
Consider antidepressants at the lowest effective dose if there
is no response to psychosocial interventions.\n\n
If the woman is breastfeeding, avoid long acting
antidepressant medication such as fluoxetine.\n\n
Consult a specialist if available.</string>
    <string name="caution4">Avoid amitriptyline if possible.</string>
    <string name="caution5">SSRIs are the first choice. Overdose of TCAs such as
amitriptyline may be fatal and therefore should be avoided in
this group.\n\n
If there is an imminent risk of self-harm or suicide
(Go to » SUI), give a limited supply of antidepressants
(e.g. one week supply at a time).\n\n
Ask the person’s carers to keep and monitor medications
and to follow-up frequently to prevent medication overdose.</string>
    <string name="population">Follow treatment for depression
(PROTOCOL 1) but AVOID antidepressants
if possible, especially during
the first trimester.\n\n
 If no response to psychological treatment,
consider using with caution the
lowest effective dose of antidepressants.\n\n
 If breastfeeding, avoid long acting
medication such as fluoxetine.\n\n
 CONSULT A SPECIALIST, if available.</string>
    <string name="dosing1">Start 25 mg at bedtime.\n
Increase by 25-50 mg per week to 100-150 mg
daily (maximum 300 mg).\n
Note: Minimum effective dose in adults is 75 mg.
Sedation may be seen at lower doses.\n\n
Elderly/Medically Ill: Start 25 mg at bedtime to
50-75 mg daily (maximum 100 mg).\n\n
Children/Adolescents: Do not use. </string>
    <string name="side1">Common: Sedation, orthostatic hypotension (risk of fall),
blurred vision, difficulty urinating, nausea, weight gain,
sexual dysfunction.\n\n
Serious: ECG changes (e.g. QTc prolongation), cardiac
arrhythmia, increased risk of seizure.</string>
    <string name="cautions1">Avoid in persons with cardiac disease, history of seizure,
hyperthyroidism, urinary retention, or narrow angle-closure glaucoma,
and bipolar disorder (can trigger mania in people with untreated bipolar
disorder).\n\n
Overdose can lead to seizures, cardiac arrhythmias, hypotension,
coma, or death.\n\n
Levels of amitriptyline may be increased by anti-malarials including
quinine.</string>

    <string name="dosing2">Start 10 mg daily for one week then 20 mg daily.
If no response in 6 weeks, increase to 40 mg
(maximum 80 mg).\n\n
Elderly/medically ill: preferred choice.
Start 10 mg daily, then increase to 20 mg
(maximum 40 mg).\n\n
Adolescents\n
Start 10 mg daily. Increase to 20 mg daily if no
response in 6 weeks (maximum 40 mg).</string>

    <string name="side2">Common: Sedation, insomnia, headache, dizziness,
gastrointestinal disturbances, changes in appetite, and
sexual dysfunction.\n\n
Serious: bleeding abnormalities in those who use
aspirin or other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, low
sodium levels.</string>
    <string name="cautions2">Caution in persons with history of seizure.\n\n
Drug-Drug interactions: Avoid combination with warfarin
(may increase bleeding risk). May increase levels of TCAs, antipsychotics,
and beta-blockers.\n\n
Caution in combination with tamoxifen, codeine, and tramadol (reduces
the effect of these drugs).</string>
    <string name="child_adolescent">CHILD / ADOLESCENT</string>
    <string name="adolescent">For management of depression in children/adolescents, go to CMH.</string>
    <string name="populations">Note that interventions may differ for these populations</string>
    <string name="_2_1_psychocarers">2.1 Psychoeducation: key messages to the person and the carers</string>
    <string name="psy_protocol2.1">Key messages for the person and their carers:\n\n
Explain that the symptoms are due to a mental health
condition, that psychosis and bipolar disorders can be
treated, and that the person can recover. Clarify common
misconceptions about psychosis and bipolar disorder.\n\n
Do not blame the person or their family or accuse them
of being the cause of the symptoms.\n\n
Educate the person and the family that the person needs
to take the prescribed medications and return for follow-up
regularly.\n\n
Explain that return and/or worsening of symptoms are
common and that it is important to recognize these early
and visit to the health facility as soon as possible.\n\n
Plan a regular work or school schedule that avoids sleep
deprivation and stress for both the person and the carers.
Encourage the person to solicit advice about major decisions
    especially ones involving money or major commitments.\n\n
    Recommend avoiding alcohol, cannabis or other nonprescription
drugs, as they can worsen the psychotic or
bipolar symptoms.\n\n
Advise them about maintaining a healthy lifestyle, e.g. a
balanced diet, physical activity, regular sleep, good personal
hygiene, and no stressors. Stress can worsen psychotic
symptoms. Note: Lifestyle changes should be continued as long
as needed, potentially indefinitely. These changes should be
planned and developed for sustainability.</string>
    <string name="psytip1">Mutual trust between the person and the
health-care provider is critical to ensure
treatment adherence and long-term outcomes.</string>
    <string name="psy_protocol2.6">If patient is on antidepressants – DISCONTINUE
to prevent further risk of mania.
– Begin treatment with lithium, valproate, carbamazepine,
or with antipsychotics. Consider a short term (2-4 weeks
maximum) benzodiazepine for behavioural disturbance or
agitation.(see Table 3).</string>
    <string name="Lithium">consider using lithium as first line treatment of
bipolar disorder only if clinical and laboratory monitoring are
available, and prescribe only under specialist supervision. If
laboratory examinations are not available or feasible, lithium
should be avoided and valproate or carbamazepine should
be considered. Erratic compliance or stopping lithium
treatment suddenly may increase the risk of relapse. Do not
prescribe lithium where the lithium supply may be frequently
interrupted. Obtain kidney and thyroid function, complete
blood count, ECG, and pregnancy tests before beginning
treatment if possible.</string>
    <string name="Valproate">Consider these
medications if clinical or laboratory monitoring for lithium is
not available or if specialist is not available to supervise
lithium prescription.</string>
    <string name="Haloperidol">consider haloperidol and
risperidone only if no clinical or laboratory monitoring is
available to start lithium or valproate. Risperidone can be
used as an alternative to haloperidol in individuals with
bipolar mania if availability can be assured, and cost is not a
constraint.</string>
    <string name="psy_caution1">For women who are pregnant or breastfeeding, avoid
valproate, lithium and carbamazepine. Use of low-dose
haloperidol is recommended with caution and under the
care of a specialist, if available.</string>
    <string name="psy_2.6">Persons with mania who are experiencing agitation may
benefit from short-term ( 2-4 weeks maximum) use of a
benzodiazepine such as diazepam.\n
– Benzodiazepines should be discontinued gradually as soon
as symptoms improve, as tolerance can develop.\n\n
Continue maintenance treatment for at least 2 years
after the last bipolar episode.\n
– Lithium or valproate can be offered for the maintenance
treatment of bipolar disorder. If treatment with one of
these agents is not feasible, haloperidol, chloropromazine
or carbamazepine may be used. Offer maintenance
treatment in primary care settings under specialist
supervision.</string>
    <string name="psy_protocol2.3">Continue regular social, educational and occupational
activities as much as possible. It is best for the person to have
a job or to be otherwise meaningfully occupied.\n\n
Facilitate inclusion in economic activities, including culturally
appropriate supported employment.\n\n
Offer life skills training and/or social skills training to enhance
independent living skills for people with psychosis and bipolar
disorders and for their families and/or carers.\n\n
Facilitate, if available and needed, independent living and
supported housing that is culturally and contextually appropriate
in the community.</string>
    <string name="psy_protocol">Ensure safety of the person and safety of others.\nProvide regular follow-up.\n
 Support rehabilitation in the community.</string>

    <string name="psy_protocol2.2">Coordinate with available health and social resources to meet
the family’s physical, social, and mental health needs.\n\n
Identify the person’s prior social activities that, if reinitiated,
would have the potential to provide direct or indirect psychological
and social support, e.g. family gatherings, outings with
friends, visiting neighbors, social activities at work sites, sports,
and community activities. Encourage the person to resume
these social activities and advise family members about this.\n\n
Encourage the person and carers to improve social
support systems.</string>
    <string name="psy_tip2">Ensure persons with psychosis are
treated with respect and dignity. For
further details go to » ECP.</string>
    <string name="psy_protocol2.5">Start with a low dose within the therapeutic range and
increase slowly to the lowest effective dose, in order to reduce
the risk of side-effects.</string>
    <string name="psy_protocol2.51">Antipsychotics should routinely be offered to a person
with psychosis.\n\n
Start antipsychotic medication immediately. See Table 1.\n\n
Prescribe one antipsychotic at a time.\n\n
Start at lowest dose and titrate up slowly to reduce risk of
side effects.\n\n
Try the medication at a typically effective dose for at
least 4-6 weeks before considering it ineffective.\n\n
Continue to monitor at that dose as frequently as possible and
as required for the first 4-6 weeks of therapy. If there is no
improvement, see Follow-up and Table 4.\n\n
Monitor weight, blood pressure, fasting sugar, cholesterol and
ECG for persons on antipsychotics if possible (see below).</string>
<string name="psy_caution2">Side effects to look for:\n\n
– Extrapyramidal side effects (EPS): akathisia, acute
dystonic reactions, tremor, cog- wheeling, muscular rigidity,
and tardive dyskinesia. Treat with anticholinergic medications
when indicated and available (see Table 2).\n\n
– Metabolic changes: weight gain, high blood pressure,
increased blood sugar and cholesterol.\n\n
– ECG changes (prolonged QT interval): monitor ECG
if possible.\n\n
– Neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS): a rare,
potentially life-threatening disorder characterized by muscular
rigidity, elevated temperature, and high blood pressure.</string>
    <string name="psy_special1">Liaise with maternal health specialists to organize care.\n\n
Consider consultation with mental health specialist if available.\n\n
Explain the risk of adverse consequences for the mother and her baby, including obstetric
complications and psychotic relapses, particularly if medication stopped.\n\n
Consider pharmacological intervention when appropriate and available. See below.</string>
    <string name="psy_special2">In women with psychosis who are planning
a pregnancy or pregnant or breastfeeding,
low-dose oral haloperidol, or chlorpromazine
may be considered.\n\n
Anticholinergics should NOT prescribed
to women who are pregnant due to extrapyramidal
side-effects of antipsychotic medications,
except in cases of acute, short-term use.\n\n
 Depot antipsychotics should not be routinely
prescribed to women with psychotic disorders
who are planning a pregnancy, pregnant, or
breastfeeding because there is relatively little
information on their safety in this population.</string>
    <string name="psy_special3">AVOID VALPROATE, LITHIUM and
CARBAMAZEPINE during pregnancy and
breastfeeding due to the risk of birth defects.\n\n
 Consider low-dose haloperidol with caution
and in consultation with a specialist, if available.\n\n
        Weigh the risks and benefits of medications in
women of childbearing age.\n\n
 If a pregnant woman develops acute mania
while taking mood stabilizers, consider switching
to low dose haloperidol.</string>
    <string name="psy_special4">Consider consultation with mental health
specialist.\n\n
In adolescents with psychotic or bipolar
disorder, risperidone can be offered as a
treatment option only under supervision of
a specialist.\n\n
If treatment with risperidone is not feasible,
haloperidol or chlorpromazine may be
used only under supervision of a specialist.</string>
    <string name="psy_special5">Use lower doses of medication.\n\n
Anticipate an increased risk of drug-drug
interactions.</string>
    <string name="psy_caution3">Antipsychotics carry an increased risk of
cerebrovascular events and death in older
adults with dementia-related psychosis.</string>

    <string name="psy_dosing1.1">Start 1.5-3 mg daily.\n
Increase as needed (maximum 20 mg daily).\n
Route: oral (p.o.) or intramuscular (i.m.).</string>
    <string name="psy_side1.1">Common: sedation, dizziness, blurred vision,
dry mouth, urinary retention, constipation.\n\n
Serious: orthostatic hypotension, extrapyramidal side
effects (EPS), ECG changes (prolonged QT interval),
weight gain, galactorrhea, amenorrhea, Neuroleptic
malignant syndrome (NMS).</string>
    <string name="psy_cau1.1">Caution in patients with: kidney disease, liver disease,
cardiac disease, long QT syndrome or taking QT-prolonging medications.
Monitor ECG if possible.</string>
    <string name="psy_dosing1.2">Start 1 mg daily.\n
Increase to 2-6 mg daily (maximum 10 mg).\n
Route: p.o.</string>
    <string name="psy_side1.2">Common: sedation, dizziness, tachycardia.\n\n
Serious: orthostatic hypotension, metabolic effects (elevated
lipids, insulin resistance, weight gain), EPS, elevated prolactin,
sexual dysfunction, NMS.</string>
    <string name="psy_cau1.2"> Caution in patients with: cardiac disease.\n\n
Drug-drug interactions: carbamazepine can reduce levels of
risperidone, whereas fluoxetine can increase levels.</string>

    <string name="psy_dosing1.3">Start 25-50 mg daily.\n
Increase to 75-300 mg daily (up to 1000 mg
may be necessary for severe cases).\n
Route: p.o.</string>
    <string name="psy_side1.3">Common: sedation, dizziness, blurred vision, dry mouth,
urinary retention, constipation, tachycardia.\n\n
Serious: orthostatic hypotension, syncope, EPS,
photosensitivity, weight gain, galactorrhea, amenorrhea,
sexual dysfunction, priapism, NMS, agranulocytosis,
jaundice.</string>
    <string name="psy_cau1.3">Contraindications: impaired consciousness, bone marrow depression,
pheochromocytoma.\n\n
Caution in patients with: respiratory disease, kidney disease, liver
disease, glaucoma, urinary retention, cardiac disease, long QT syndrome
or taking QT-prolonging medications. Monitor ECG if possible.\n\n
Drug-drug interactions:\n
– Increases effects of blood pressure lowering medications.\n
– Lowers blood pressure if combined with epinephrine.\n
– Levels may be increased by antimalarials including quinine.</string>
    <string name="psy_dosing1.4">Start 12.5 mg.\n
Use 12.5-50 mg every 2-4 weeks.\n
Route: i.m. in gluteal region.\n\n
    Avoid in women who are pregnant/
breastfeeding.\n\n
Do not use in children/adolescents.</string>
    <string name="psy_side1.4">Common: sedation, dizziness, blurred vision, dry mouth,
urinary retention, constipation, tachycardia.\n\n
Serious: orthostatic hypotension, syncope, EPS,
photosensitivity, weight gain,galactorrhea, amenorrhea,
sexual dysfunction, priapism, NMS, agranulocytosis,
jaundice.</string>
    <string name="psy_cau1.4">Contraindications: impaired consciousness, parkinsonism.\n\n
Caution in patients with: cardiac disease, kidney disease, liver disease.
Use with caution in older adults.\n\n
Drug-drug interactions:\n
– Increases effects of blood pressure lowering medications.\n
– Can lower blood pressure if used with epinephrine.</string>
    <string name="psy_dosing2.1">Start 1 mg twice daily.\n
Increase to 3-12 mg daily.\n
Route: p.o or intravenous (i.v.).</string>
    <string name="psy_side2.1">Common: sedation, confusion and memory
disturbance (especially in older adults), tachycardia, dry
mouth, urinary retention and constipation.\n
Rarely, angle-closure glaucoma, myasthenia gravis and
gastrointestinal obstruction.</string>
    <string name="psy_cau2.1">Caution in patients with: cardiac, liver, or kidney disease.\n\n
Drug-drug interactions: Caution when combining with other
anticholinergic medications.</string>
    <string name="psy_dosing2.2">Start 1 mg daily.\n
Increase to 4-12 mg per day in 3-4 divided doses
(maximum 20 mg daily).\n
Route: p.o </string>

    <string name="psy_dosing3.1"> Start 300 mg daily. Increase gradually every
7 days until target blood level reached (maximum
600-1200 mg daily). Monitor every 2-3 months.\n
Route: p.o\n\n
Target blood levels: 0.6-1.0 mEq/liter
– In acute manic episode: 0.8-1.0 mEq/liter
– For maintenance treatment: 0.6-0.8 mEq/liter.\n\n
6 months on medication is needed to determine full
effectiveness of maintenance treatment.</string>
    <string name="psy_side3.1">Common: sedation, cognitive problems, tremor, :
impaired coordination, hypotension, leukocytosis,
polyuria, polydipsia, nausea, diarrhea, weight gain, hair
loss, rash.\n\n
Serious: diabetes insipidus, hypothyroidism,
ECG changes (arrhythmia, sick sinus syndrome, T-wave
changes). </string>
    <string name="psy_cau3.1">Contraindicated in patients with: severe cardiac or kidney disease.\n\n
Dehydration can increase lithium levels.\n\n
Drug-drug interactions: nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs),
angiotensin-converting-enzyme inhibitor (ACE inhibitor), thiazide diuretics,
metronidazole, and tetracycline can increase lithium levels.\n\n
Lithium toxicity can cause seizures, delirium, coma, and death. </string>
    <string name="psy_dosing3.2">Start 500 mg daily.\n
Increase slowly to 1000-2000 mg daily
(maximum 60 mg/kg/day).\n
Route: p.o\n\n
Preferred choice in persons living with
HIV/AIDS due to drug-drug interactions.</string>
    <string name="psy_side3.2">Common: sedation, headache, tremor, ataxia, nausea,
vomiting, diarrhea, weight gain, transient hair loss.\n\n
Serious: impaired hepatic function, thrombocytopenia,
leucopenia, drowsiness/confusion, liver failure,
hemorrhagic pancreatitis.</string>
    <string name="psy_cau3.2">Caution in patients with: underlying or suspected hepatic disease.
Monitor liver function tests and platelets if possible.\n\n
Drug-drug interactions:\n
Valproate levels decreased by carbamazepine, increased by aspirin.</string>
    <string name="psy_dosing3.3">Start 200 mg daily.\n
Increase by 200 mg weekly to 400-600 mg daily in
two divided doses (maximum 1200 mg daily).\n
Route: p.o\n\n
Note: Dose may need to be adjusted after
2 weeks due to induction of its own metabolism.</string>
    <string name="psy_side3.3">Common: sedation, confusion, dizziness, ataxia,
double vision, nausea, diarrhea, benign leucopenia.\n\n
Serious: hepatotoxicity, cardiac conduction delay, low
sodium levels, severe rash.</string>
    <string name="psy_cau3.3">Contraindicated in patients with: history of blood disorders,
kidney, liver, or cardiac disease.\n\n
Drug-drug interactions.\n
– May reduce the effects of hormonal birth control, immunosuppressants,
antiepileptics, antipsychotics, methadone and some antiretrovirals.\n
– Levels can be increased by certain antifungals and antibiotics.</string>

    <string name="phy_clinical1.1">
The person is not tolerating antipsychotic
medication, i.e. the person has
extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS) or other
serious side effects
</string>


    <string name="psy_action1.1">
Reduce the dose of antipsychotic medication.\n
If side-effects persist, consider switching to another antipsychotic medication.\n
Consider adding anticholinergic medication for short-term use to treat EPS if these strategies fail or if symptoms are severe (see Table 2).

</string>

    <string name="psy_clinical2.1">Adherence to treatment is
unsatisfactory</string>


    <string name="psy_action2.1">
Discuss reasons for non-adherence with the person and carers.\n
And provide information regarding importance of medication.\n
Consider depot/long-acting injectable antipsychotic medication as an option after discussing possible side effects of oral versus
depot preparations.

</string>

    <string name="psy_clinical3.1">
Treatment response is inadequate
(i.e. symptoms persist or worsen) despite
adherence to medication
</string>
    <string name="psy_action3.1">
Verify that the person is receiving an effective dose of medication. If the dose is low, increase gradually to lowest effective dose to reduce
the risk of side effects.\n
Enquire about alcohol or substance use and take measures to reduce this. Go to » SUB.\n
Enquire about recent stressful event that may have led to worsening of clinical condition and take measures to reduce stress.
Review symptoms to rule out physical and/or other priority MNS conditions. Go to » PSY 1, see STEP 1\n
Consider risperidone as an alternative to haloperidol or chlorpromazine, if cost and availability are not constraints.\n
If the person does not respond to adequate dose and duration of more than one antipsychotic medication, using one medicine at a time,
then antipsychotic combination treatment may be considered; preferably under the supervision of a specialist, with close clinical monitoring.\n
Consider consultation with a specialist for the use of clozapine in those who have not responded to other antipsychotic medications
at adequate doses and durations. Only use clozapine under the supervision of a specialist and only if routine laboratory monitoring is available,
due to the risk of life-threatening agranulocytosis.


</string>

    <string name="psy_ass">Attempt to communicate with the person.\n
Evaluate for underlying cause:\n\n
– Check Blood Glucose. If low, give glucose.\n
– Check vital signs, including temperature and oxygen
saturation. Give oxygen if needed.\n
– Rule out delirium and medical causes
including poisoning.\n
– Rule out drug and alcohol use.\n
Specifically consider stimulant intoxication and/or
alcohol/sedative withdrawal. Go to SUB.\n
– Rule out agitation due to psychosis or manic
episode in bipolar disorder. Go to Assessment,
» PSY 1.</string>
    <string name="psy_com">Safety is first!\n\n
Remain calm and encourage the patient to talk
about his or her concerns.\n\n
Use a calm voice and try to address the concerns
if possible.\n\n
Listen attentively. Devote time to the person.\n\n
Never laugh at the person.\n\n
Do not be aggressive back.\n\n
Try to find the source of the problem and solutions
for the person.\n\n
Involve carers and other staff members.\n\n
Remove from the situation anyone who may be a
trigger for the aggression.\n\n
If all possibilities have been exhausted and the person
is still aggressive, it may be necessary to use medication
(if available) to prevent injury.</string>
    <string name="psy_sed">Sedate as appropriate to prevent injury.\n\n
For agitation due to psychosis or mania, consider use of haloperidol
2mg p.o./i.m. hourly up to 5 doses (maximum 10 mg).
Caution: high doses of haloperidol can cause dystonic reactions.
Use biperiden to treat acute reactions.\n\n
For agitation due to ingestion of substances, such as
alcohol/sedative withdrawal or stimulant intoxication,
use diazepam 10-20 mg p.o. and repeat as needed. Go to SUB.\n\n
In cases of extreme violence\n
– Seek help from police or staff\n
– Use haloperidol 5mg i.m., repeat in 15-30mins if needed
(maximum 15 mg)\n\n
– Consult a specialist.
if the person remains agitated, recheck oxygen saturation,
vital signs and glucose. Consider pain. Refer to hospital.\n\n
Once agitation subsides, refer to the master chart (MC) and
select relevant modules for assessment.\n\n
Special Populations:\n
Consult a specialist for treatment.</string>
    <string name="epi_topic1">Provide information on: "What is a convulsion/epilepsy" and the importance of medication. \n\n

    </string>

    <string name="epi_protocol_2_1">
        “A convulsion is caused by excess electrical activity in the brain – it is not caused by witchcraft or spirits.” \n\n
        “Epilepsy is the recurrent tendency for convulsions.” \n\n
        “It is a chronic condition, but if you take your medicine as prescribed, in the majority of people it can be fully controlled.” \n\n
         The person may have several people helping them take care of their convulsions. Discuss this with the person. \n\n
         Ask the person to let you know if they are seeing a traditional or a faith healer, showing respect for this, but emphasizing the
         need for being seen at a healthcare facility. The person should also be informed that medicines and herbal products can sometimes have adverse interactions,
        so the health care providers must know about everything they take. \n\n
     </string>

    <string name="epi_clinical_tip">
        Seizures lasting greater than 5 minutes are  a medical emergency – one should seek help immediately. \n\n
        Most people with epilepsy can have normal lives with good adherence to treatment. \n\n
        </string>


    <string name="epi_topic2">Provide information on: How carers can manage convulsion at home. \n\n

    </string>

    <string name="epi_protocol2_1">
        Lay person down, on their side, head turned to help breathing. \n\n

        DO NOT PUT ANYTHING IN THEIR MOUTH OR RESTRAIN THE PERSON. \n\n

        Ensure the person is breathing properly. \n\n
        Stay with person until the convulsion stops and they wake up. \n\n
        Sometimes people with epilepsy know that a convulsion is imminent. They should lie down somewhere safe if they have that feeling. \n\n
        Epilepsy is not contagious. You cannot catch the disorder by assisting the person experiencing convulsions. \n\n

      </string>

    <string name="epi_topic3">Provide information on: When to get medical help. \n\n</string>

    <string name="epi_protocol__2_1">
        When a person with epilepsy appears to have trouble breathing during a convulsion, they need immediate  medical help. \n\n
        When a person with epilepsy has a convulsion lasting longer than 5 minutes outside of a health facility,
        they need to be taken to one. \n\n
        When a person with epilepsy is not waking up after a convulsion, they need to be taken to a health facility. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_protocol_2_3">Choose a medication that will be consistently available. \n\n
              If special population (children, women of childbearing age, person living with HIV), see relevant section of this module. \n\n
              Start with only one medication at lowest starting dose. \n\n
              Increase dose slowly until convulsions are controlled. \n\n
              Consider monitoring blood count, blood chemistry and  liver function tests, if available. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_protocol_2_2">Refer to Essential Care and Practice (ECP) for interventions that promote functioning in daily living and community life. \n\n
                                       In addition, inform carers and people  with epilepsy that:  \n\n
                                        –  People with epilepsy can lead normal lives.  They can marry and have children. \n
                                        –  Parents should not remove children with epilepsy from school.  \n
                                        –  People with epilepsy can work in most jobs. However they should avoid jobs with high risk of injury to self or others (e.g. working with heavy machinery).  \n
                                        –  People with epilepsy should avoid cooking on open ﬁres and swimming alone.  \n
                                        –  People with epilepsy should avoid excessive alcohol and recreational substances, sleeping too little, or going to places with ﬂashing lights.  \n
                                        –  Local driving laws related to epilepsy should be observed. \n
                                        – People with epilepsy may qualify for disability beneﬁts.  \n
                                        –  Community programs for people with epilepsy can provide assistance in jobs and support for both the person and family.


    </string>

    <string name="epi_population">Note that interventions are different for EPILEPSY in these populations.

    </string>

    <string name="epi_childbearing1">  Advise folate (5 mg/day) to prevent neural tube  defects, in ALL women of childbearing age. \n\n
                                       AVOID VALPROATE. \n\n
                                       CAUTION If Pregnant: \n\n
                                        –  Avoid polytherapy. Multiple medications in combination increase the risk of teratogenic effects during pregnancy. \n
                                        –   If medications are stopped during pregnancy,  they should always be tapered. \n
                                        – Advise delivery in hospital. \n
                                        –  At delivery, give 1 mg vitamin K i.m. to the newborn to prevent haemorrhagic disease. \n\n
                                       If breastfeeding, carbamazepine preferred to other medication
    </string>

    <string name="epi_child_adol1"> For those with a developmental disorder,  manage the condition. Go to >>CMH. \n\n
                                    For children with behavioural disorder, avoid phenobarbital if possible. Manage the condition.  Go to>>CMH. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_hiv_perso1">   When available, refer to speciﬁc drug interactions  for person’s antiretroviral regimen and antiepileptic medication. \n \n
                                     Valproate is preferred due to fewer drug-drug interactions. \n \n
                                     AVOID PHENYTOIN AND CARBAMAZEPINE  WHEN POSSIBLE. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_caution">  Check for drug-drug interactions. When used together, antiepileptics may increase or reduce the effect of other antiepilepileptics. Antiepileptics may also reduce effect of hormonal birth control, immunosuppressants, antipsychotics, methadone, and some antiretrovirals.  \n\n
                                 Rarely, can cause severe bone marrow depression, hypersensitivity reactions including Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, altered Vitamin D metabolism and Vitamin K-deﬁcient hemorrhagic disease of newborns. \n\n
                                 When possible, avoid use of sodium valproate in pregnant women due to risk of neural tube defects. \n\n
                                 All anticonvulsant medications should be discontinued slowly as stopping them abruptly can cause seizure breakthrough. \n\n
</string>


    <string name="epi_oraldosing1">Adults: \n\n
    Start 100-200 mg daily in 2-3 divided doses. \n
    Increase by 200 mg each week (max 1400mg daily). \n\n

    Children: \n\n
    Start 5 mg/kg daily in 2-3 divided doses. Increase by 5 mg/kg daily each week (max 40mg/kg daily OR 1400mg daily). \n\n

    Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding: Use with caution.
</string>

    <string name="epi_sideeffect1">Common: Sedation, confusion, dizziness, ataxia double vision, nausea, diarrhea, benign leukopenia. \n\n
                    Serious: Hepatotoxicity, cardiac conduction delay,  low sodium levels \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_caution1">Caution in patients with history of blood disorders, kidney,  liver or cardiac disease. \n\n
                    Dose may need to be adjusted after 2 weeks due to induction of  its own metabolism. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_oraldosing2"> Adults: \n\n
                Start 60 mg daily in 1-2 divided doses.   Increase weekly by 2.5-5 mg (maximum 180 mg daily). \n\n
                Children: \n\n
                Start 2-3 mg/kg daily in 2 divided doses. \n
                Increase weekly by 1-2 mg/kg daily depending  on tolerance (maximum 6mg daily).
</string>
    <string name="epi_sideeffect2">Common: Sedation, hyperactivity in children, ataxia, nystagmus, sexual dysfunction, depression. \n\n
                                Serious: Liver failure (hypersensitivity reaction), decreased bone mineral density. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_caution2"> Contraindicated in patients with acute intermittent porphyria. \n\n
    Lower doses for patients with kidney or liver disease. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_oraldosing3"> Adults: \n
        Start 150-200 mg daily in two divided doses. Increase by 50 mg daily every 3-4 weeks  (max 400 mg daily). \n\n

        Children: \n
        Start 3-4 mg/kg daily in 2 divided doses.   Increase by 5 mg/kg daily every 3-4 weeks (maximum 300 mg per day). \n\n
          Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding: Avoid \n\n
          Older adults: Use lower doses \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_sideeffect3"> Common: Sedation, confusion, dizziness, tremor, motor twitching, ataxia, double vision, nystagmus, slurred speech, nausea, vomiting, constipation. \n\n
                            Serious: Hematologic abnormalities, hepatitis, polyneuropathy, gum hypertrophy, acne, lymphadenopathy, increase in suicidal ideation.
    </string>

    <string name="epi_caution3">Lower doses for patients with kidney or liver disease.
    </string>

    <string name="epi_oraldosing4"> Adults: \n
        Start 400 mg daily in 2 divided doses. Increase by 500 mg daily each week  (maximum 3000 mg daily). \n\n
        Children: \n
        Start 15-20 mg/kg daily in 2-3 divided doses. Increase each week by 15 mg/kg daily  (max 15-40 mg/kg daily). \n\n
        Women who are pregnant: Avoid \n\n
        Older adults: Use lower doses \n\n
    </string>
    <string name="epi_sideeffect4">Common: Sedation, headache, tremor, ataxia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, weight gain, transient hair loss. \n\n
            Serious: Impaired hepatic function, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, drowsiness/confusion (valproate-induced hyperammonemic encephalopathy, a sign of toxicity),  liver failure, hemorrhagic pancreatitis. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="epi_caution4">Use with caution if underlying or suspected hepatic disease. \n\n
        Drug-drug interactions: Valproate levels decreased by carbamazepine, increased by aspirin.
    </string>





    <string name="bev_2_1_cmh">  Spend time with their child in enjoyable activities.  Play and communicate with their child/adolescent.  http://www.who.int/maternal_child_adolescent/documents/ care_child_development/en/ \n\n

     Listen to the child/adolescent and show understanding  and respect. \n\n
     Protect them from any form of maltreatment, including bullying and exposure to violence in the home, at school, and in the community. \n\n
     Anticipate major life changes (such as puberty, starting school, or birth of a sibling) and provide support. \n\n

    </string>

    <string name="bev_2_1_cmh_p1">    Get enough sleep. Promote regular bed routines and remove TV or other electronic devices  with screens from the sleeping area/bedroom. \n\n
     Eat regularly. All children/adolescents need three meals (breakfast, mid-day, and evening) and some snacks each day. \n\n
     Be physically active. If they are able, children and adolescents aged 5–17 should do 60 minutes or more of physical activity each day through daily activities, play, or sports. See www.who.int/dietphysicalactivity/publications/ recommendations5_17years \n\n
     Participate in school, community, and other social activities as much as possible. \n\n
     Spend time with trusted friends and family. \n\n
     Avoid the use of drugs, alcohol, and nicotine. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="bev_2_2_cmh">    Explain the delay or difﬁculty to the carer and the child/ adolescent as appropriate and help them identify strengths and resources. \n\n
     Praise the carer and the child/adolescents for their efforts. \n\n
     Explain to the carer that parenting a child/adolescent with an emotional, behavioural or developmental delay or disorder can be rewarding but also very challenging. \n\n
    Explain that persons with mental disorders should not be blamed for having the disorder. Encourage carers to be kind and supportive and show love and affection. \n\n
    Promote and protect human rights of the person and the family and be vigilant about maintaining human rights and dignity.\n\n
    Help carers to have realistic expectations and encourage them to contact other carers of children/adolescents with similar conditions for mutual support. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="bev_2_3_cmh"> Give loving attention, including playing with the child every day.  Provide opportunities for the adolescents to talk to you. \n\n
     Be consistent about what your child/adolescent is allowed and not allowed to do. Give clear, simple, and short instructions on what the child should and should not do. \n\n
     Give the child/adolescent simple daily household tasks to do that match their ability level and praise them immediately after they do the task. \n\n
     Praise or reward the child/adolescent when you observe good behaviour and give no reward when behaviour is problematic. \n\n
     Find ways to avoid severe confrontations or foreseeable difﬁcult situations. \n\n
     Respond only to the most important problem behaviours and make punishment mild (e.g. witholding rewards and fun activities) and infrequent compared to the amount of praise. \n\n
     Put off discussions with the child/adolescent until you are calm. Avoid using criticism, yelling, and name-calling. \n\n
      DO NOT use threats or physical punishment, and never physically abuse the child/adolescent. Physical punishment can harm the child-carer relationship; it does not work as well as other methods and can make behaviour problems worse. \n\n
     Encourage age-appropriate play (e.g. sports, drawing or other hobbies) for adolescents and offer age-appropriate support in practical ways (e.g. with homework or other  life skillls). \n\n
 </string>

    <string name="bev_2_6_cmh">    Assess the psychosocial impact of the child/adolescent’s disorders on the carers, and offer support for their personal, social, and mental health needs. \n\n
     Promote necessary support and resources for their family life, employment, social activities, and health. \n\n
     Arrange for respite care (trustworthy carers taking over  care on a short term basis) to give primary carers a break, especially if the child has a developmental disorder. \n\n
     Support family to handle social and familial problems and help to problem solve. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="bev_2_7_cmh">    After getting consent from the child/adolescent and carer, contact the child/adolescent’s teacher and provide advice/ make a plan on how to support the child with learning and participation in school activities. \n\n
     Explain that the child/adolescent’s mental disorder is affecting their learning/behaviour/social functioning and that there are things the teacher can do to help. \n\n
     Ask about any stressful situations that may have an adverse impact on the child’s emotional well-being and learning. If the child is being bullied, advise the teacher on appropriate action to stop it. \n\n
     Explore strategies to help engage the child in school activities and facilitate learning, inclusion, and participation. \n\n
     Simple tips: \n\n
 –  Provide opportunities for the child/adolescent to use  their skills and strengths. \n
 –  Ask the student to sit at the front of the class. \n
 –  Give the student extra time to understand and complete assignments. \n
 –  Divide long assignments into smaller pieces and assign  one piece at a time. \n
 –  Provide extra praise for effort and rewards for achievements.  –   DO NOT use threats or physical punishments or  excessive criticism. \n
 –  For students with signiﬁcant difﬁculties in the classroom, recruit a volunteer to come to class to provide one-on-one attention or pair the student with a peer who can provide support or help with learning. \n
 –  If the child/adolescent has been out of school, help them return as soon as possible by creating a gradually increasing reintegration schedule. During the reintegration period, the student should be excused from quizzes and exams. \n

    </string>

    <string name="bev_2_8_cmh"> This guide does not provide speciﬁc protocols to implement  brief psychological interventions, such as parent skills training, interpersonal therapy and behavioural therapy. WHO has developed Parent Skills Training package for caregivers of children with developmental delay/disorders and is available  on request.

    </string>

    <string name="bev_2_8_cmhp1"> This guide does not provide speciﬁc protocols to implement  brief psychological interventions, such as parent skills training, interpersonal therapy and behavioural therapy. WHO has developed Parent Skills Training package for caregivers of children with developmental delay/disorders and is available  on request.

    </string>

    <string name="bev_2_1_cmhproto2">  Spend time with their child in enjoyable activities.  Play and communicate with their child/adolescent.  http://www.who.int/maternal_child_adolescent/documents/ care_child_development/en/ \n\n

     Listen to the child/adolescent and show understanding  and respect. \n\n
     Protect them from any form of maltreatment, including bullying and exposure to violence in the home, at school, and in the community. \n\n
     Anticipate major life changes (such as puberty, starting school, or birth of a sibling) and provide support. \n\n

    </string>

    <string name="bev_2_1_cmh_proto">    Get enough sleep. Promote regular bed routines and remove TV or other electronic devices  with screens from the sleeping area/bedroom. \n\n
     Eat regularly. All children/adolescents need three meals (breakfast, mid-day, and evening) and some snacks each day. \n\n
     Be physically active. If they are able, children and adolescents aged 5–17 should do 60 minutes or more of physical activity each day through daily activities, play, or sports. See www.who.int/dietphysicalactivity/publications/ recommendations5_17years \n\n
     Participate in school, community, and other social activities as much as possible. \n\n
     Spend time with trusted friends and family. \n\n
     Avoid the use of drugs, alcohol, and nicotine. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="bev_2_2_cmhproto2">    Explain the delay or difﬁculty to the carer and the child/ adolescent as appropriate and help them identify strengths and resources. \n\n
     Praise the carer and the child/adolescents for their efforts. \n\n
     Explain to the carer that parenting a child/adolescent with an emotional, behavioural or developmental delay or disorder can be rewarding but also very challenging. \n\n
    Explain that persons with mental disorders should not be blamed for having the disorder. Encourage carers to be kind and supportive and show love and affection. \n\n
    Promote and protect human rights of the person and the family and be vigilant about maintaining human rights and dignity.\n\n
    Help carers to have realistic expectations and encourage them to contact other carers of children/adolescents with similar conditions for mutual support. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="bev_2_7_cmhproto2">    After getting consent from the child/adolescent and carer, contact the child/adolescent’s teacher and provide advice/ make a plan on how to support the child with learning and participation in school activities. \n\n
     Explain that the child/adolescent’s mental disorder is affecting their learning/behaviour/social functioning and that there are things the teacher can do to help. \n\n
     Ask about any stressful situations that may have an adverse impact on the child’s emotional well-being and learning. If the child is being bullied, advise the teacher on appropriate action to stop it. \n\n
     Explore strategies to help engage the child in school activities and facilitate learning, inclusion, and participation. \n\n
     Simple tips: \n\n
 –  Provide opportunities for the child/adolescent to use  their skills and strengths. \n
 –  Ask the student to sit at the front of the class. \n
 –  Give the student extra time to understand and complete assignments. \n
 –  Divide long assignments into smaller pieces and assign  one piece at a time. \n
 –  Provide extra praise for effort and rewards for achievements.  –   DO NOT use threats or physical punishments or  excessive criticism. \n
 –  For students with signiﬁcant difﬁculties in the classroom, recruit a volunteer to come to class to provide one-on-one attention or pair the student with a peer who can provide support or help with learning. \n
 –  If the child/adolescent has been out of school, help them return as soon as possible by creating a gradually increasing reintegration schedule. During the reintegration period, the student should be excused from quizzes and exams. \n

    </string>

    <string name="bev_2_1_cmhproto3">  Spend time with their child in enjoyable activities.  Play and communicate with their child/adolescent.  http://www.who.int/maternal_child_adolescent/documents/ care_child_development/en/ \n\n

     Listen to the child/adolescent and show understanding  and respect. \n\n
     Protect them from any form of maltreatment, including bullying and exposure to violence in the home, at school, and in the community. \n\n
     Anticipate major life changes (such as puberty, starting school, or birth of a sibling) and provide support. \n\n

    </string>

    <string name="bev_2_1_cmh_proto3">    Get enough sleep. Promote regular bed routines and remove TV or other electronic devices  with screens from the sleeping area/bedroom. \n\n
     Eat regularly. All children/adolescents need three meals (breakfast, mid-day, and evening) and some snacks each day. \n\n
     Be physically active. If they are able, children and adolescents aged 5–17 should do 60 minutes or more of physical activity each day through daily activities, play, or sports. See www.who.int/dietphysicalactivity/publications/ recommendations5_17years \n\n
     Participate in school, community, and other social activities as much as possible. \n\n
     Spend time with trusted friends and family. \n\n
     Avoid the use of drugs, alcohol, and nicotine. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="bev_2_2_cmhproto3">    Explain the delay or difﬁculty to the carer and the child/ adolescent as appropriate and help them identify strengths and resources. \n\n
     Praise the carer and the child/adolescents for their efforts. \n\n
     Explain to the carer that parenting a child/adolescent with an emotional, behavioural or developmental delay or disorder can be rewarding but also very challenging. \n\n
    Explain that persons with mental disorders should not be blamed for having the disorder. Encourage carers to be kind and supportive and show love and affection. \n\n
    Promote and protect human rights of the person and the family and be vigilant about maintaining human rights and dignity.\n\n
    Help carers to have realistic expectations and encourage them to contact other carers of children/adolescents with similar conditions for mutual support. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="bev_2_3_cmhproto3"> Give loving attention, including playing with the child every day.  Provide opportunities for the adolescents to talk to you. \n\n
     Be consistent about what your child/adolescent is allowed and not allowed to do. Give clear, simple, and short instructions on what the child should and should not do. \n\n
     Give the child/adolescent simple daily household tasks to do that match their ability level and praise them immediately after they do the task. \n\n
     Praise or reward the child/adolescent when you observe good behaviour and give no reward when behaviour is problematic. \n\n
     Find ways to avoid severe confrontations or foreseeable difﬁcult situations. \n\n
     Respond only to the most important problem behaviours and make punishment mild (e.g. witholding rewards and fun activities) and infrequent compared to the amount of praise. \n\n
     Put off discussions with the child/adolescent until you are calm. Avoid using criticism, yelling, and name-calling. \n\n
      DO NOT use threats or physical punishment, and never physically abuse the child/adolescent. Physical punishment can harm the child-carer relationship; it does not work as well as other methods and can make behaviour problems worse. \n\n
     Encourage age-appropriate play (e.g. sports, drawing or other hobbies) for adolescents and offer age-appropriate support in practical ways (e.g. with homework or other  life skillls). \n\n
 </string>
    <string name="bev_2_5_cmhproto6">    Address any stressful situation in the family environment such as parental discord or a parent’s mental disorder. With the help of teachers explore possible adverse circumstances in the school environment. \n\n
     Provide opportunities for quality time with the carer and  the family. \n\n
     Encourage and help the child/adolescent to continue  (or restart) pleasurable and social activities. \n\n
     Encourage the child/adolescent to practice regular physical activity, gradually increasing the duration of sessions. \n\n
     Consider training the child/adolescent and carer in breathing exercises, progressive muscle relaxation and other cultural equivalents. \n\n
     Make predictable routines in the morning and at bedtime. Promote regular sleep habits. Schedule the day with regular times for eating, playing, learning, and sleeping. \n\n
     For excessive and unrealistic fears: \n\n
    –  Praise the child/adolescent or give small rewards when they try new things or act bravely. \n
    –  Help the child practice facing the difﬁcult situation one small step at a time (e.g. if the child is afraid of separating from the carer, help the child gradually increase the amount of time he/she plays alone while the carer is nearby). \n
    –  Acknowledge the child’s feelings and worries and encourage them to confront their fears. \n
    –  Help the child/adolescent create a plan to help them cope in case a feared situation occurs. \n
     Explain that emotional disorders are common and can happen to anybody. The occurrence of emotional disorders does not mean that the person is weak or lazy. \n\n
     Emotional disorders can cause unjustiﬁed thoughts of hopelessness and worthlessness. Explain that these views are likely to improve once the emotional disorders improve. \n\n
     Make the  person aware that if they notice thoughts of self-harm or suicide, they should tell a trusted person and come back for help immediately. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="sui_proto1"> For all cases: Place the person in a  secure and supportive environment at a health facility</string>

    <string name="sui_2_1proto1"> Medically treat injury or poisoning.  If there is acute pesticide intoxication, follow “Management of pesticide intoxication”.</string>

    <string name="sui_2_1">If the health care facility has a minimum set of skills and resources, then treat using the WHO document, “Clinical Management of Acute Pesticide Intoxication” (http://www. who.int/mental_health/publications/9789241596732/en). \n\n
  Otherwise, transfer the person immediately to a health facility that has the following resources: \n\n
 –  Skills and knowledge on how to resuscitate individuals  and assess for clinical features of pesticide poisoning; \n
 –  Skills and knowledge to manage the airway; in particular, to intubate and support breathing until a ventilator can  be attached; \n
 –  Atropine and means for its intravenous (i.v.) administration if signs of cholinergic poisoning develop; \n
 –  Diazepam and means for its i.v. administration if the person develops seizures. \n\n
   Consider administering activated charcoal if the person  is conscious, gives informed consent, and presents for care within one hour of the poisoning. \n\n
   Forced vomiting is not recommended. \n\n
    Oral ﬂuids should not be given. \n\n

    </string>

    <string name="sui_2_2"> Place the person in a secure and supportive environment  at a health facility ( do not leave them alone). If the person must wait for treatment, offer an environment that minimizes distress; if possible, in a separate,
        quiet room  with constant supervision and contact with a designated staff or family member to ensure safety at all times. \n\n
   Remove access to means of self-harm. \n\n
   Consult a mental health specialist, if available. \n\n
   Mobilize family, friends and other concerned individuals or available community resources to monitor and
        support the person during the imminent risk period (see “Offer and activate psychosocial support”. (2.3) \n\n
   Treat people who have self-harmed with the same care, respect and privacy given to other people, and be sensitive to the emotional distress associated with self-harm. \n\n
   Include the carers if the person wants their support during assessment and treatment; if possible, the psychosocial assessment should include a one-to-one interview between the person and the health worker, to explore private issues. \n\n
   Provide emotional support to carers/family members if they need it. (2.4) \n\n
   Ensure continuity of care. \n\n
   Hospitalization in non-psychiatric services of a general hospital is not recommended for the prevention of self-harm. However, if admission to a general (non-psychiatric) hospital is necessary for the management of the medical consequences of self-harm, monitor the person closely to prevent further self-harm in the hospital. \n\n
    If prescribing medication: \n\n
 –  See relevant mhGAP-IG modules for pharmacological interventions in the management of concurrent conditions. \n
 –  Use medicines that are the least hazardous, in case  of intentional overdose. \n
 –  Give prescriptions as short courses (e.g. one week  at a time). \n

    </string>

    <string name="sui_2_3">Offer support to the person \n\n
 – Explore reasons and ways to stay alive. \n
 –  Focus on the person’s strengths by encouraging them to talk of how earlier problems have been resolved. \n
 –  Consider problem-solving therapy to help people with acts of self-harm within the last year, if sufﬁcient human resources are available. Go to Essential care and practice  ECP
     Activate psychosocial support \n
 –  Mobilize family, friends, concerned  individuals and other available resources to ensure close monitoring of the person as long as the risk of self-harm/suicide persists. \n
 –  Advise the person and carers to restrict access to means  of self-harm/suicide (e.g. pesticides/toxic substances, prescription medications, ﬁrearms, etc.) when the person has thoughts or plans of self-harm/suicide. \n
 –  Optimize social support from available community resources. These include informal resources, such as relatives, friends, acquaintances, colleagues and religious leaders or formal community resources, if available, such  as crisis centres, and local mental health centres. \n
</string>

    <string name="sui_2_4">
    Inform carers and family members that asking about suicide will often help the person feel relieved, less anxious, and better understood. \n\n
    Carers and family members of people at risk of self-harm often experience severe stress. Provide emotional support to them if they need it. \n\n
    Inform carers that even though they may feel frustrated  with the person, they should avoid hostility and severe criticism towards the vulnerable person at risk of self-harm/suicide. \n\n
</string>

    <string name="sui_proto2">Create a secure and supportive environment;  if possible, offer a separate, quiet room while waiting for treatment.

    </string>

    <string name="sui_2_5_proto2">  Key messages to the person and the carers: \n\n
 –  If one has thoughts of self-harm/suicide, seek help immediately from a trusted family member, friend or health care provider. \n
 –  It is okay to talk about suicide. Talking about suicide does not provoke the act of suicide. \n
 –  Suicides are preventable. \n
 –  Having an episode of self-harm/suicide is an indicator of severe emotional distress. The person does not see an alternative or a solution. Therefore, it is important to get the person immediate support for emotional problems and stressors. \n
 –  Means of self-harm (e.g. pesticides, ﬁrearms, medications) should be removed from the home. \n
 –  The social network, including the family and relevant others, is important for provision of social support. \n
</string>

    <string name="sui_2_3_proto2">Offer support to the person: \n\
 – Explore reasons and ways to stay alive. \n
 –  Focus on the person’s strengths by encouraging them to talk of how earlier problems have been resolved. \n
 –  Consider problem-solving therapy to help people with acts of self-harm within the last year, if sufﬁcient human resources are available. Go to Essential care and practice  ECP. \n\n
     Activate psychosocial support: \n\
 –  Mobilize family, friends, concerned  individuals and other available resources to ensure close monitoring of the person as long as the risk of self-harm/suicide persists. \n
 –  Advise the person and carers to restrict access to means  of self-harm/suicide (e.g. pesticides/toxic substances, prescription medications, ﬁrearms, etc.) when the person has thoughts or plans of self-harm/suicide. \n
 –  Optimize social support from available community resources. These include informal resources, such as relatives, friends, acquaintances, colleagues and religious leaders or formal community resources, if available, such  as crisis centres, and local mental health centres. \n
</string>

    <string name="sui_2_4_proto2">   Inform carers and family members that asking about suicide will often help the person feel relieved, less anxious, and better understood. \n\n
   Carers and family members of people at risk of self-harm often experience severe stress. Provide emotional support to them if they need it. \n\n
   Inform carers that even though they may feel frustrated  with the person, they should avoid hostility and severe criticism towards the vulnerable person at risk of self-harm/suicide. \n\n

    </string>

    <string name="sui_2_3_proto3">Offer support to the person: \n\
 – Explore reasons and ways to stay alive. \n
 –  Focus on the person’s strengths by encouraging them to talk of how earlier problems have been resolved. \n
 –  Consider problem-solving therapy to help people with acts of self-harm within the last year, if sufﬁcient human resources are available. Go to Essential care and practice  ECP. \n\n
     Activate psychosocial support: \n\
 –  Mobilize family, friends, concerned  individuals and other available resources to ensure close monitoring of the person as long as the risk of self-harm/suicide persists. \n
 –  Advise the person and carers to restrict access to means  of self-harm/suicide (e.g. pesticides/toxic substances, prescription medications, ﬁrearms, etc.) when the person has thoughts or plans of self-harm/suicide. \n
 –  Optimize social support from available community resources. These include informal resources, such as relatives, friends, acquaintances, colleagues and religious leaders or formal community resources, if available, such  as crisis centres, and local mental health centres. \n
</string>
</resources>
