<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="Disorder1">
        1) \n
        Does the person appear sedated?
    </string>
    <string-array name="Disorder_emergency_yes">
      <item>  1) \n
        Does the person appear sedated?
        </item>
        <item>
            Suspect SEDATIVE INTOXICATION  (alcohol, opioids, other sedatives) \n
            - Check Airway, Breathing, Circulation (ABC). \n
            - Provide initial respiratory support. \n
            - Give oxygen. \n \n
            Is the person minimally responsive, unresponsive,  or in respiratory failure?
        </item>
        <item>
            - Supportive care. \n
            - Monitor vital signs. \n
            - Lay the person on their side to prevent aspiration. \n
            - Give oxygen if available. \n
            - Consider intravenous (i.v.), rehydration but do not give fluids orally while sedated. \n
            - Observe the person until fully recovered or  transported to hospital. \n \n
            Check pupils. \n \n
            Normal pupils-NO \n
              Opioid overdose less likely
            –  consider overdose of alcohol, other sedatives, or other medical causes
            (i.e. head injury, infection, or hypoglycemia). \n \n

            Pinpoint pupils \n Suspect  OPIOID OVERDOSE \n\n
        </item>
        <item>
            Give i.v., intramuscular (i.m.), intranasal  or subcutaneous naloxone 0.4-2 mg. \n
            Continue respiratory support. \n \n
            Did the person respond to naloxone within 2 minutes? \n\n
        </item>
        <item>
            Observe for 1-2 hours and repeat naloxone  as needed.    \n
            Continue to resuscitate and observe the person until fully recovered or transported to hospital. \n \n
            2) \n
            Does the person appear  overstimulated, anxious, or agitated?
        </item>
        <item>
            ASSESS AND MANAGE FROM A to D. \n
            Or Continue to next Step.
        </item>
        <item>3) \n
            Does the person appear confused?
        </item>
        <item>
            Are there any medical conditions which might  explain the confusion, including: \n
           – head trauma \n
            – hypoglycaemia \n
            – pneumonia or other infections \n
             – hepatic encephalopathy \n
            – cerebrovascular accidents (CVA) \n
        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="Disorder_emergency_no">
      <item>
       SKIP to STEP  2
      </item>
        <item>2) \n
            Does the person appear  overstimulated, anxious, or agitated? \n
        </item>
        <item>
              >> Check pupils. \n \n
            Normal pupils-NO \n
              Opioid overdose less likely
            –  consider overdose of alcohol, other sedatives, or other medical causes
            (i.e. head injury, infection, or hypoglycemia). \n \n

            Pinpoint pupils-YES \n
            Suspect  OPIOID OVERDOSE
        </item>
        <item>
            Give i.v., intramuscular (i.m.), intranasal  or subcutaneous naloxone 0.4-2 mg. \n
            Continue respiratory support. \n \n
            Did the person respond to naloxone within 2 minutes?
        </item>
        <item>
                GIVE A SECOND DOSE   \n
            Observe the person until fully recovered or transported to hospital. \n
            2 \n
            Does the person appear  overstimulated, anxious, or agitated?
        </item>
        <item>
            SKIP to SUB 1 Assessment
        </item>
        <item>
               Manage the physical condition  and refer the person to hospital.
        </item>
    </string-array>


    <string-array name="AcessA_D">
        <item> A)\n
            Person has recently stopped drinking or using sedatives and is now showing any of the following signs:
            Tremors, sweating, vomiting, increased blood pressure (BP) and heart rate, and agitation. \n \n

            Suspect  ALCOHOL, BENZODIAZEPINE OR OTHER SEDATIVE WITHDRAWAL \n \n
                MANAGE WITHDRAWAL  \n \n
            –  If the person has tremors, sweating, or vital sign changes then give diazepam 10-20 mg orally (p.o.)
                and transfer to hospital or detoxiﬁcation  facility if possible.  \n
            –  Observe and repeat doses as needed for continued signs of  withdrawal (tremors, sweating, increased BP and heart rate). \n
            –  For alcohol withdrawal only: Give thiamine 100 mg daily for ﬁve days. \n \n

            TRANSFER IMMEDIATELY TO A HOSPITAL  \n  if the following are present:  \n
            –  Other serious medical problems, e.g. hepatic encephalopathy, gastrointestinal bleeding, or head injury. \n
            –  Seizures: give diazepam 10-20 mg p.o., i.v. or rectum (p.r.) ﬁrst. \n
            –  Delirium: give diazepam 10-20 mg p.o., i.v. or p.r. ﬁrst. If severe and not responsive to diazepam, give an
               anti-psychotic medication such as haloperidol 1-2.5 mg p.o. or i.m. Continue to treat other signs of withdrawal
               (tremors, sweating, vital signs changes) with diazepam p.o., i.v. or p.r. \n
        </item>
        <item>B) \n
            Person has recently used stimulants (cocaine, amphetamine type stimulants (ATS) or other stimulants) and is showing any of
            the following signs: dilated pupils, anxiety, agitation, hyper-excitable state, racing thoughts, raised pulse and
            blood pressure. \n \n

            Suspect  ACUTE STIMULANT INTOXICATION \n \n
            -  Give diazepam 5-10 mg p.o., i.v., or p.r.  in titrated doses until the person is calm and lightly sedated. \n
            -  If psychotic symptoms are not responsive to diazepam, consider antipsychotic medication such as haloperidol
            1-2.5 mg p.o. or i.m.. Treat until symptoms resolve. If symptoms persist, go to  PSYCHOSES. \n
            -  For management of persons with aggressive and/or agitated behaviour  go to PSYCHOSES, Table 5. \n
            -  If the person has chest pain, tachyarrythmias, or other neurological signs TRANSFER TO HOSPITAL. \n
            -  During the post-intoxication phase, be alert for suicidal thoughts or actions. If suicidal thoughts are present, go to SUICIDE. \n
        </item>
        <item>C) \n
        Person has recently stopped using opioids and is showing any of the following signs: dilated pupils, muscle aches,
            abdominal cramps, headache, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, runny eyes and nose, anxiety, restlessness. \n \n
            Suspect  ACUTE OPIOID WITHDRAWAL \n \n

               MANAGE OPIOID WITHDRAWAL \n \n
            –  Methadone 20 mg, with a supplemental dose of 5-10 mg 4 hours later if necessary. \n
            –  Buprenorphine 4-8 mg, with a supplementary dose 12 hours later if necessary. \n
            –  If methadone or buprenorphine are not available, any opioid can  be used in the acute setting, i.e. morphine \n
               sulphate 10-20 mg as an initial dose with a 10 mg extra dose if needed. Also consider an alpha adrenergic agonists,
                i.e. clonidine or lofexidine. \n
            -  Once stable, go to  SUBSTANCE USE 2 \n
        </item>
        <item>
            D) \n
            RULE OUT OTHER MEDICAL CAUSES AND PRIORITY MNS CONDITIONS.
        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="AssesA_C">
        <item>A \n
        Person has stopped drinking in the last week: confusion, hallucination, racing thoughts, anxiety, agitation, disorientation,
            typically in association with either stimulant intoxication or alcohol (or other sedative) withdrawal. \n\n
            Suspect  ALCOHOL OR SEDATIVE WITHDRAWAL DELIRIUM \n
                 If the person is showing other signs of alcohol or sedative withdrawal (tremors, sweating, vital signs changes)
            – Treat with diazepam 10-20 mg p.o. as needed. \n
            – TRANSFER TO HOSPITAL.     \n
            Manage delirium  with antipsychotics such as  haloperidol 1-2.5 mg p.o. or i.m.
        </item>
        <item>B \n
            Person has been drinking heavily in the last few days AND has any of the folllowing signs:  \n
            –  nystagmus (involuntary, rapid and repetitive movement of the eyes) \n
            –  ophthalmoplegia  (weakness/paralysis of one or more of the muscles that control eye movement) \n
            – ataxia (uncoordinated movements). \n \n
            Suspect  WERNICKE’S ENCEPHALOPATHY \n \n
               Treat with thiamine 100-500 mg 2-3 times daily i.v. or i.m. for 3-5 days. \n
               TRANSFER TO HOSPITAL.
        </item>
        <item>C \n
        Person has used stimulants in the last few days: Dilated pupils, excited, racing thoughts, disordered thinking, strange behaviour,
            recent use of psychoactive substances, raised pulse and blood pressure, aggressive, erratic, or violent behaviour. \n \n
            Suspect  STIMULANT OR HALLUCINOGEN INTOXICATION \n
            -   Treat with diazepam 5-10 mg p.o., i.v. or p.r. until the patient is lightly sedated. \n
            -   If psychotic symptoms do not respond to diazepam, consider  an antipsychotic such as haloperidol 1-2.5 mg p.o. or i.m. \n
            -   If psychotic symptoms persist, go to  PSY \n
        </item>
    </string-array>

    <string name="Asessment_1">
        1) \n
        Does the person use substances? \n \n
        Ask about use of tobacco, alcohol, and psychoactive prescription medicines.
        Depending on the setting and the presentation, consider asking about cannabis and other substance use.
    </string>

    <string-array name="DISORDERS_Asessment_yes">
        <item>
            1) \n
            Does the person use substances? \n \n
        Ask about use of tobacco, alcohol, and psychoactive prescription medicines.
        Depending on the setting and the presentation, consider asking about cannabis and other substance use.
        </item>
        <item>
        2) \n
        Is the substance use harmful? \n For each substance used assess: \n\n
            <b>A</b>  Frequency and quantity of use. <i> (Hint: Ask “How many days per week do you use this substance? How much do you use per day?”)</i>  \n \n
            <b>B</b>  Harmful behaviours. <i>(Hint: Ask “Does your substance use cause you any problems?”)</i> \n \n
            –  Injuries and accidents \n
            – Driving while intoxicated \n
            – Drug injection, sharing needles, reusing needles \n
            – Relationship problems as a result of use \n
            –  Sexual activity while intoxicated that was risky  or later regretted  \n
            – Legal or ﬁnancial problems \n
            – Inability to care for children responsibly \n
            – Violence towards others \n
            – Poor performance in education, employment roles \n
            –  Poor performance in expected social roles   (e.g. parenting) \n
        </item>
        <item>3)  \n
        <b>Is DEPENDENCE likely? </b> \n \n

       For each substance used ask about the following features of dependence: \n
            –  High levels of <i>frequent substance </i> use \n
            –  A strong craving or sense of compulsion to  use the substance \n
            –  Difﬁculty self regulating the use of that substance despite the risks and harmful consequences \n
            –  Increasing levels of use tolerance and withdrawal symptoms on cessation
        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="DISORDERS_Asessment_No">
        <item>
               - Emphasise the health beneﬁts of not using psychoactive substances.  \n
               - EXIT MODULE
        </item>
        <item>
            Is the substance use harmful?  \n
        <i> See answer in step 2, above.</i>
        </item>
        <item>
           - Provide psychoeducation about the risks of different levels of each substance used. \n
           - EXIT MODULE
        </item>
    </string-array>
    <string name="DISORDERS_followup">
        1)\n
        ASSESS FOR IMPROVEMENT \n \n
                At every visit, assess: \n
            -  Quantity and frequency of substance use, mental health, physical  health, risk and protective factors (e.g. relationships,
            accommodation,  employment, etc.) \n
            -  Ask about factors that lead to substance use and consequences  of substance use \n \n
             <b>ONGOING SUBSTANCE USE</b> \n
             -  Develop strategies to reduce harm \n
             -  Treat health problems \n
             -  Develop strategies to reduce use \n
             -  Arrange detoxiﬁcation or maintenance treatment if client agrees \n
             -  Conduct frequent review and outreach \n \n
            <b>RECENT CESSATION OF USE  OR SHIFT TO NON-HARMFUL USE</b> \n
            -  Consider urine testing to conﬁrm abstinence \n
            -   Give positive feedback to encourage the maintenance of abstinence/non-harmful use \n
            -   Treat other medical problems \n
            -   Consider relapse prevention medications for alcohol and opioid dependence \n
            -   Consider psychosocial therapies to prevent relapse and mutual help groups \n
            -   Support factors which reduce the risk of relapse such as housing and employment \n
            <b> LONG TERM CESSATION OR  NON-HARMFUL USE</b> \n \n
            -   Consider occasional urine testing to conﬁrm non-use \n
            -   Positive feedback \n
            -   Support factors which reduce the risk of  relapse (such as housing and employment) \n
            -   Treat other medical problems \n
            -   Encourage participation in mutual help groups \n
            -   less frequient reviews

    </string>
</resources>